import { Question } from '../shared/src/index';

export const LABOR_LAW_QUESTIONS: Question[] = [
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 1,
        "Question": "What is the foundation of the agrarian reform program under the 1987 Constitution? Who are the direct beneficiaries of the program?",
        "Answer": "The 1987 Constitution enunciates in Article II as one of the state policies that '(t)he State shall promote comprehensive rural development and agrarian reform. In Article XII of the Constitution, in dealing with the national economy and patrimony, it is also stated that (t)he State shall promote industrialization and full employment based on sound agricultural development and agrarian reform, x x x Then in Article XIII of the Constitution, in dealing with social justice and human rights, there is this provision, among others- 'The State shall, by law, undertake an agrarian reform program founded on the right of farmers and regular farm-workers, who are landless, to own directly or collectively the lands they till or in the case of other farmworkers, to receive a just share of the fruits thereof. To this end. the State shall encourage and undertake the just distribution of all agricultural lands, subject to such priorities and reasonable retention limits as the Congress may prescribe, taking into account ecological, developmental, or equity considerations, and subject to the payment of just compensation. In determining the retention limits, the State shall respect the right of small landowners. The State shall further provide incentives for voluntary landsharing. Taken togetner, the above provisions could be considered as the foundation of the agrarian reform program. Under the Comprehensive Agrarian Reform Law, the lands covered by the Comprehensive Agrarian Reform Program shall be distributed as much as possible to landless residents of the same barangay. or in the absence thereof, landless residents of the same municipality in the following order of priority."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 2,
        "Question": "Is there any distinction between labor legislation and social legislation?",
        "Answer": "Labor legislation is sometimes distinguished from social legislation by the former referring to labor statutes, like Labor Relations Law and Labor Standards, and the latter to Social Security Laws. Labor legislation focuses on the rights of the worker in the workplace. Social legislation is a broad term and may include not only laws that give social security protection, but also those that help the worker secure housing and basic necessities. The Comprehensive Agrarian Reform law could also be considered a social legislation. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: Yes. Labor Legislation is limited in scope, and deals basically with the rights and duties of employees and employers. Social Legislation is more encompassing and includes such subjects as agrarian relations, housing and human settlement, protection of women and children, etc. All labor laws are social legislation, but not all social legislation is labor law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 3,
        "Question": "Clarito, an employee of Juan, was dismissed for allegedly stealing Juan’s wristwatch. In the illegal dismissal case instituted by Clarito, the Labor Arbiter, citing Article 4 of the Labor Code, ruled in favor of Clarito upon finding Juan’s testimony doubtful. On appeal, the NLRC reversed the Labor Arbiter holding that Article 4 applies only when the doubt involves 'implementation and interpretation' of the Labor Code provisions. The NLRC explained that the doubt may not necessarily be resolved in favor of labor since this case involves the application of the Rules on Evidence, not the Labor Code. Is the NLRC correct? Reasons.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The NLRC is not correct. It is a well settled doctrine that if doubts exist between the evidence presented by the employer and the employee, the scale of justice must be tilted in favor of the latter. It is a time honored rule that in controversies between laborer and master, doubts necessarily arising from the evidence, or in the implementation of the agreement and writing should be resolved in favor of the laborer. ANOTHER SUGGESTED ANSWER: No, the NLRC is not correct. Art. 221 of the Labor Code read: 'In any proceeding before the Commission....the rules of evidence prevailing in Courts of law....shall not be controlling and it is the spirit and intention of this Code that the Commission and its members and the Labor Arbiters shall use every and reasonable means to ascertain the facts in each case speedily and objectively without regard to technicalities of law and procedure, all in the interest of due process.' The question of doubt is not important in this case."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 4,
        "Question": "Which takes precedence in conflicts arising between employers’ MANAGEMENT PREROGATIVE and the employees’ right to security of tenure? Why?",
        "Answer": "The employee's right to security of tenure takes precedence over the employer's management prerogative. Thus, an employer's management prerogative includes the right to terminate the services of an employee but this management prerogative is limited by the Labor Code which provides that the employer can terminate an employee only for a just cause or when authorized by law. This limitation on management prerogative is because no less than the Constitution recognizes and guarantees an employee’s right to security of tenure. (Art. 279. Labor Code: Art. XIII, Sec. 3. Constitution)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 5,
        "Question": "Enumerate at least four (4) policies enshrined in Section 3, Article XIII of the Constitution that are not covered by Article 3 of the Labor Code on declaration of basic policy.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Four (4) policies enshrined in Section 3, Article XIII of the 1987 Constitution which are not covered by Article 3 of the Labor Code on declaration of basic policy are: 1. All workers shall have the right to peaceful concerted activities, including the right to strike in accordance with law. 2. They shall be entitled to a living wage. 3. They shall participate in policy and decision making processes affecting their rights and benefits as may be provided by law. 4. The state shall promote the principle of shared responsibility between workers and employers."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 6,
        "Question": "In her State of the Nation Address, the President stressed the need to provide an investor-friendly business environment so that the country can compete in the global economy that now suffers from a crisis bordering on recession. Responding to the call, Congress passed two innovative legislative measures, namely: (1) a law abolishing the security of tenure clause in the Labor Code; and (2) a law allowing contractualization in all areas needed in the employer’s business operations. However, to soften the impact of these new measures, the law requires that all employers shall obtain mandatory unemployment insurance coverage for all their employees. The constitutionality of the two (2) laws is challenged in court. As judge, how will you rule?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The first innovative measure, on abolition of the security of tenure clause in the Labor Code, is unconstitutional as it goes against the entitlement of workers to security of tenure under Section 3, Article XIII of the 1987 Constitution. The second innovative measure, on a law allowing contractualization in all areas needed in the employer’s business operations, is legal. Article 106 of the Labor Code already allows the Secretary of Labor and Employment not to make appropriate distinction between labor-only and job contracting. This means that the Secretary may decide, through implementing regulation, not to prohibit labor-only contacting, which is an arrangement where the person supplying workers to an employer does not have substantial capital or investment in the form of tools, equipment, machineries, work premises, among others, and the workers recruited and place by such person are performing activities which are directly related to the principal business of the employer. Hence, it would be legal for Congress to do away with the prohibition on labor-only contracting and allow contractualization in all areas needed in the employer’s business operations. Assuming, of course, that contractual workers are guaranteed their security of tenure."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 7,
        "Question": "Deeds of release, waivers and quitclaims are always valid and binding.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "FALSE. Deeds of release, waivers and quitclaims are not always valid and binding. An agreement is valid and binding only if: (a) the parties understand the terms and conditions of their settlement; (b) it was entered into- freely and voluntarily by them; and (c) it is contrary to law, morals, and public policy. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: FALSE. Not all deeds of release, waivers and quitclaims are valid and binding. The Supreme Court, in Periquet v. NLRC (186 SCRA 724 ) and affirmed in Solgus Corporation v. Court of Appeals (514 SCRA 522 ), provided the following guideposts in determining the validity of such release, waivers and quitclaims: 'Not all waivers and quitclaims are invalid as against public policy. If the agreement was voluntarily entered into and represents a reasonable settlement, it is binding on the parties and may not later be disowned simply because of a change of mind. But where it is shown that the person making the waiver did so voluntarily, with full understanding of what he was doing, and the consideration for the quitclaim is credible and reasonable, the transaction must be recognized as a valid and binding undertaking.'"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 8,
        "Question": "The Independence Bank of the Philippines (IBP) is the mortgage creditor of San Juan Trading Company (SJTC). For failure of SJTC to pay its obligations, IBP foreclosed the former’s mortgaged properties and in the bidding acquired the properties as the highest bidder. SJTC’s workers, whose claims for separation pay, unpaid wages and other benefits could not be satisfied, filed an action against IBP to enforce their claims, contending that they enjoyed preference in respect of separation pay, wages and other benefits due them prior to the cessation of SJTC's operations. Will the action of the workers against IBP prosper? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The action of the workers against IBP will not prosper. It is true that the Labor Code provides: In the event of bankruptcy or liquidation of an employer's business, his workers shall enjoy first preference as regards their wages and other monetary claims, any provisions of law to the contrary notwithstanding. Such unpaid wages and monetary claim shall be paid in full before claims of the government and other creditors may be paid. But, here, the mortgaged property is no longer owned by SJTC. The first preference of the workers can only be enforced against the judgement debtor, meaning SJTC, and not against IBC who now owns the mortgaged property which has been fore-closed. (Development Dank of the Philippines vs. Minister of Labor and Employment, et al. G.R. No. 75801, March 20,1991)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 9,
        "Question": "XYZ Company filed a petition for bankruptcy before a Regional Trial Court. Among the list of creditors are the Philippine National Bank (PNB), various suppliers, the Bureau of Internal Revenue (BIR) for payment of back taxes and the Union in representation of the employees for unpaid wages, leaves and bonuses. a. With regards to the other creditors, particularly the PNB and BIR, what is the standing of the employees claims? b. Would it make any difference if there is no judicial declaration of bankruptcy?",
        "Answer": "a. In Republic v. Peralta, the claims of the 'Government, like the taxes that should be paid to the BIR, should first be paid before the money claims of the workers. But if, the question is now resolved under Rep. Act No. 6715, it is now provided that 'unpaid wages and monetary claims (of workers) shall be paid in full before the claims of the Government and the other creditors may be paid. b. If there is no judicial declaration of bankruptcy, the claim of the Union in representation of the employees for unpaid wages, leaves and bonuses will be given preference after there is a finding by a Labor Arbiter, hearing the case as a money claim, that an employer is bankrupt."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 10,
        "Question": "Which is not a constitutional right of the workers? (2012 Bar) a. The right to engage in peaceful concerted activities; b. The right to enjoy security of tenure; c. The right to return on investment; d. The right to receive a living wage.",
        "Answer": "c) The right to return on investment [Art. XIII, Sec. 3, Constitution]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 11,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct with respect to the extent of the application of security of tenure? (2012 Bar Question) a. It applies to managerial and to all rank-and-file employees if not yet regular, but not to management trainees; b. It applies to managerial and to all rank-and-file employees including those under probation; c. It applies to seasonal and project employees, if they are hired repeatedly; d. It applies to all kinds of employees except those employed on a part-time basis.",
        "Answer": "a. It applies to managerial and to all rank-and-file employees if not yet regular, but not to management trainees. [Management Trainee are not employees yet]. b. It applies to managerial and to all rank-and-file employees including those under probation"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 12,
        "Question": "Mr. Del Carmen, unsure if his foray into business (messengerial service catering purely to law firms) would succeed but intending to go long-term if he hurdles the first year, opted to open his operations with one-year contracts with two law firms although he also accepts messengerial service requests from other firms as their orders come. He started with one permanent secretary and six (6) messengers on a one-year, fixed-term, contract. Is the arrangement legal from the perspective of labor standards? (2013 Bar Questions) (A) No, because the arrangement will circumvent worker's right to security of tenure. (B) No. If allowed, the arrangement will serve as starting point in weakening the security of tenure guarantee. (C) Yes, if the messengers are hired through a contractor. (D) Yes, because the business is temporary and the contracted undertaking is specific and time-bound. (E) No, because the fixed term provided is invalid.",
        "Answer": "(A)  ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: (E) Reason: The employer and employee must deal with each other on more or less equal terms."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 13,
        "Question": "What is the quantum of evidence required in labor case? (2012 Bar Question) a. The degree of proof which produces the conclusion that the employee is guilty of the offense charged in an unprejudiced mind; b. Such amount of relevant evidence which a reasonable mind might accept as adequate to justify a conclusion; c. That degree of proof which is greater in weight than the opposing party’s evidence; d. Such evidence which must be highly and substantially more probable to be true than not which convinces the trier of facts of its factuality.",
        "Answer": "b. Such amount of relevant evidence which a reasonable mind might accept as adequate to justify a conclusion. [Tancirco vs. GSIS, G.R. No. 132916, Nov. 16, 2001]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 14,
        "Question": "Procopio was dismissed from employment for stealing his co-employee Raul's watch. Procopio filed a complaint for illegal dismissal. The Labor Arbiter ruled in Procopio's favor on the ground that Raul's testimony was doubtful, and, therefore, the doubt should be resolved in favor of Procopio. On appeal, the NLRC reversed the ruling because Article 4 of the Labor Code - which states that all doubts in the interpretation and implementation of the provisions of the Labor Code, including the implementing rules and regulations, shall be resolved in favor of labor - applied only when the doubt involved the implementation and interpretation of the Labor Code; hence, the doubt, which involved the application of the rules on evidence, not the Labor Code, could not necessarily be resolved in favor of Procopio. Was the reversal correct? Explain your answer.  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The reversal is not correct. Article 227 (221) of the Labor Code clearly provides that the rules of evidence prevailing in courts of law shall not be controlling in any proceeding before the NLRC or the Labor Arbiters. Moreover, the NLRC/Labor Arbiters are mandated to use every and all reasonable means to ascertain the facts speedily and objectively and without regard to technicalities of law or procedure, all in the interest of due process."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 15,
        "Question": "In what manner do the labor laws show its solicitous compassionate policy towards the working man? Explain your answer.",
        "Answer": "Labor laws show solicitous compassionate policy towards the working man by providing that all doubts in the implementation and interpretation of labor laws including its implementing rules and regulations shall be resolved in favor of labor. Thus, among others, the Constitution recognizes that workers are entitled to security of tenure, humane conditions of work and a living wage. Labor laws should be liberally interpreted to ensure that the above rights are given to workers. Many times, an employee commits an offense that is a valid ground for disciplinary action but law and jurisprudence do not automatically provide for the termination of the guilty employee because termination may be too harsh a penalty, his employment may, more often than not be the sole source of his means of livelihood. (Art. 4, Labor Code; Art. XIII. Sec. 3. Constitution)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 16,
        "Question": "What, if any, is the basis under the Constitution for adopting it? (2007 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Art. XIII, Sec. 3 of the Constitution guarantees labor their right to participate in decision and policy-making processes affecting their rights, duties and welfare. FIRST ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: The adoption of codetermination is based on the police power of the state and the constitutional mandate to the State 'to promote, the principle of shared responsibility between the workers and the employers.' The Constitution expressly provides that:'It shall guarantee the rights of all workers to xxx collective bargaining and negotiations, xxx. They shall be entitled to security of tenure, humane conditions of work, and a living wage. They shall also participate in policy and decision-making processes affecting their rights and benefits as may be provided by law.' (Art. XIII, Sec. 3, 1987 Constitution)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 17,
        "Question": "Q: What is tripartism? What is the binding effect of an agreement entered into in a tripartite conference?",
        "Answer": "Tripartism in labor relations is the policy of the State enunciated in the Labor Code (in Art. 275) which is implemented by consulting with representatives of workers and employers in the consideration and adoption of voluntary codes of principles designed to promote industrial peace ba.sed on social justice or to align labor movement relations with priorities in economic and social development. The codes of principles adopted at tripatite conferences are voluntary. They do not have a legal binding effect on workers and employers. But because these codes are considered and adopted by representatives of workers and employers, they are likely to be complied with voluntarily by workers and employers. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: Should not bind unions and employers’ organizations that were not represented in the tripartite conference because they were not parties or signatories to any agreement arrived at in the conference."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 18,
        "Question": "On December 12, 2008, A signed a contract to be part of the crew of ABC Cruises, Inc. through its Philippine manning agency XYZ. Under the standard employment contract of the Philippine Overseas Employment Administration (POEA), his employment was to commence upon his actual departure from the port in the point of hire, Manila, from where he would take a flight to the USA to join the cruise ship 'MS Carnegie'. However, more than three months after A secured his exit clearance from the POEA for his supposed departure on January 15,2009, XYZ still had not deployed him for no valid reason. Is A entitled to relief? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "YES. Even if no departure took place, the contract of employment has already been perfected which creates certain rights and obligations, the breach of which may give rise to a cause of action against the erring party: before the NLRC, despite absence of employer-employee relationship. Section 10 of Rep. Act No. 8042 conferred jurisdiction on the Labor Arbiter not only on claims arising out of EER, but also by virtue of any law or contract involving Filipino workers for overseas deployment including claims for actual, moral, exemplary and other forms of damages. (Santiago vs. CF Sharp Crew Management, 527 SCRA 165 )."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 19,
        "Question": "The State shall allow the deployment of overseas Filipino Workers only in countries where the rights of Filipino migrant workers are protected. Which of the following is not a guarantee, on the part of the receiving country, for the protection of the rights of OFW’s? (2012 Bar Question) a. It has existing labor and social laws protecting the rights of migrant workers; b. It promotes and facilitates re-integration of migrants into the national mainstream; c. It is a signatory and/or ratifier of multilateral conventions, declarations or resolutions relating to the protection of migrant workers; d. It has concluded a bilateral agreement or arrangement with the government on the protection of the rights of overseas Filipino workers.",
        "Answer": "b. It promotes and facilitates re-integration of migrants into the national mainstream. [Sec. 4 of RA 8042 as amended by Sec. 3 of RA 10022]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 20,
        "Question": "Marino Palpak, Eddie Angeles and Jose Berdugo advertised in the Manila Bulletin the following information: '20 Teachers wanted for Egypt. Apply at No. 123 Langit. Manila. Salvacion Inocente applied and was made to pay minimal fees to cover administrative expenses and the cost of her passport and visa. For one reason or another, Salvacion did not get the job and filed a complaint with the POEA. Marino, Eddie and Jose admitted having no license or authority but claimed that they are not covered by the Labor Code since they are not engaged in the recruitment and placement for profit and, at any rate, only one prospective worker was involved. May Marino, Eddie and Jose be prosecuted? If so, for what specific offense/s?",
        "Answer": "Marino Eddie and Jose can be prosecuted. Recruitment and placement by persons without a license or authority constitute illegal activities. Marino, Eddie and Jose were engaged in recruitment and placement when they advertised that 20 teachers were wanted to Egypt. Advertising for employment is one of the acts considered as recruitment and placement in the Labor Code. That they were not engaged in recruitment and placement for profit does not mean that the conditions for a person to engage in recruitment and placement found in the Labor Code are not applicable to them. The Code applies to any recruitment or placement, whether for profit or not. The fact that only one prospective worker was involved does not mean that they were not engaged in recruitment or placement. They were. The reference in the Code that any person who offers employment to 'two or more persons' as being engaged in recruitment and placement does not mean that there must be at least two persons involved. This reference is merely evidentiary. They may be prosecuted for these specific offenses: They already charged fees even if they have not yet obtained employment for the applicant."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 21,
        "Question": "A. When is illegal recruitment considered a crime of economic sabotage? Explain briefly.  B. Is a corporation, seventy percent (70%) of the authorized and voting capital of which is owned and controlled by Filipino citizens, allowed to engage in the recruitment and placement of workers, locally or overseas? Explain briefly. ",
        "Answer": "A. According to Art. 28 of the Labor Code, illegal recruitment is considered a crime of economic sabotage when committed by a syndicate or in large scale. Illegal recruitment is deemed committed by a syndicate if carried out by a group of three (3) or more persons conspiring and/or confederating with one another in carrying out any unlawful or illegal transaction, enterprise or scheme which is an act of illegal recruitment. Illegal recruitment is deemed committed in large scale if committed against three (3) or more persons individually or as a group. B. No. A corporation, seventy percent (70%) of the authorized arid, voting capital stock of which is owned and controlled by Filipino citizens cannot be permitted to participate in the recruitment and placement of workers, locally or overseas, because Art 27 of the Labor Code requires at least seventy-five percent (75%)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 22,
        "Question": "A. Rocket Corporation is a domestic corporation registered with the SEC, with 30% of its authorized capital stock owned by foreigners and 70% of its authorized capital stock owned by Filipinos. Is Rocket Corporation allowed to engage in the recruitment and placement of workers, locally and overseas? Briefly state the basis for your answer. (2015 Bar Question) B. When does the recruitment of workers become an act of economic sabotage? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "A. No. Article 27 of the Labor Code mandates that pertinently, for a Corporation to validly engage in recruitment and placement of workers, locally and overseas, at least seventy-five percent (75%) of its authorized and voting capital stock must be owned and controlled by Filipino citizens. Since only 70% of its authorized capital stock is owned by Filipinos, it consequently cannot validly engage in recruitment and placement of workers, locally and overseas. B. Illegal recruitment is considered a crime of economic sabotage when committed by a syndicate or in large scale."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 23,
        "Question": "May X be held criminally liable for illegal recruitment? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "NO. X performed his work with the knowledge that he works for a licensed recruitment agency. He is in no position to know that the officers of said recruitment agency failed to register him as its personnel (People v. Chowdury, 325 SCRA 572 [20Q0] J. The fault not being attributable to him, he may be considered to have apparent authority to represent Alpha on recruitment for overseas employment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 24,
        "Question": "May the officers having control, management or direction of Alpha Personnel Services, Inc. be held criminally liable for illegal recruitment? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Yes. Alpha, being a licensed recruitment agency, still has obligations to A for processing his papers for overseas employment. Under Section 6(m) of Rep. Act No. 8042, failure to reimburse expenses incurred by the worker in connection with his documentation and processing for purposes of deployment, in cases where the deployment does not actually take place without the worker’s fault, amounts to illegal recruitment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 25,
        "Question": "A was recruited to work abroad by Speedy Recruitment Agency as a technician for a Saudi Arabian construction firm, with a monthly salary of $650.00. When she got to the construction site, the employer compelled her to sign another contract that referred her to another employer for a salary of $350.00. She worked for the second employer and was paid $350.00 until her two-year contract expired. Upon her return to the Philippines, she filed a case against the agency and the two employers. May the agency validly raise the defense that it was not privy to the transfer of A to the second employer? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "NO. Speedy’s obligation to A is joint and several with the principal employer (Sec. 10, Rep. Act No. 8042). The liability of the principal/employer and the recruitment/placement agency for any and all claims for money claims shall be joint and several, which undertaking shall form part of A’s employment contract, and condition precedent for its approval. This liability shall continue during the entire period or duration of the employment contract and shall not be affected by any substitution, amendment or modification made locally or in a foreign country of said contract (Sec. 10, Rep. Act No. 8042)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 26,
        "Question": "What is the nature of the liabilities of the local recruitment agency and its foreign principal? (2012 Bar Question) d. Local agency is jointly liable with the foreign principal; severance of the relations between the local agent and the foreign principal does not affect the liability of the local recruiter.",
        "Answer": "Local agency is solidarily liable with the foreign principal; severance of relations between the local agent and foreign principal does not affect the liability of the foreign principal, [Section 10, second paragraph, RA 8042]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 27,
        "Question": "B. As a rule, direct hiring of migrant workers is not allowed. What are the exceptions? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The exceptions are: direct hiring by members of the diplomatic organizations, international organizations, heads of state and government officials with the rank of at least deputy minister, and such other employers as may be allowed by the Secretary of Labor (Book I, Title I, Chapter I, Article 18, Labor Code). The reasons for the ban on direct hiring are: a) A worker hired directly by a foreign employer without government intervention may not be assured of the best possible terms and conditions of employment. b) A foreign employer must also be protected. Without government intervention, a foreign employer may be entering into a contract with a Filipino who is not qualified to do the job. c) The mandatory requirement for remittance to the Philippines of a portion of the worker's foreign exchange earnings can easily be evaded by the worker."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 28,
        "Question": "C. Phil, a resident alien, sought employment in the Philippines. The employer, noticing that Phil was a foreigner, demanded that he first secures an employment permit from the DOLE. Is the employer correct? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "No, the employer is not correct. Only non-resident aliens seeking admission to the Philippines are required to obtain an employment permit from the Department of Labor and Employment (Article 40, Labor Code). ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: The employer is not correct. Under DOLE Department Order No. 75-06, resident foreign nationals are exempted from securing an employment permit."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 29,
        "Question": "Peter worked for a Norwegian cargo vessel. He worked as a deckhand, whose primary duty was to assist in cleaning the ship. He signed a five-year contract starting in 2009. In 2011, Peter’s employers began treating him differently. He was often maltreated and his salary was not released on time. These were frequently protested to by Peter. Apparently exasperated by his frequent protestations, Peter’s employer, a once top official in China, suddenly told him that his services would be terminated as soon as the vessel arrived at the next port, in Indonesia. Peter had enough money to go back home, and immediately upon arriving, he filed a money claim with the NLRC against his former employer’s local agent. Will Peter’s case prosper? (2012 Bar Question) a. Yes, he is entitled to full reimbursement of his placement fee, with interest at 12% per annum, plus salary for the unexpired portion of his employment contract or for three (3) months for every year of the unexpired portion, whichever is higher. b. Yes, he is entitled to full reimbursement of his placement fee, with interest at 12% per annum, plus his salary for the unexpired portion of his employment contract for three (3) months for every year of the unexpired portion, whichever is less; c. Yes, he is entitled to his salaries for the unexpired portion of his employment contract, plus full reimbursement of his placement fee with interest at 12% per annum; d. Yes, he is entitled to his salaries for three (3) months for every year of the unexpired portion of his unemployment contract, plus full reimbursement of his placement fee with interest at 12% per annum.",
        "Answer": "a) Yes, he is entitled to his salaries for the unexpired portion of his employment contract, plus full reimbursement of his placement fee with interest at 12% per annum [Serrano vs. Gallant Maritime, G.R. No. 167614, March 24, 2009]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 30,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. As a general rule, direct hiring of Overseas Filipino Workers (OFWs) is not allowed.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "TRUE. Art. I5 of the Labor Code provides that no employer may hire a Filipino worker for overseas employment except through the Boards and entities authorized by the Department of Labor and Employment (DOLE) except direct-hiring by members of the diplomatic corps, international organizations and such other employers as may be allowed by the DOLE. Another exemption is ‘‘Name Hire,' which refers to a worker who is able to secure an overseas employment opportunity with an employer without the assistance or participation of any agency."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 31,
        "Question": "The power suspend or cancel a license to recruit employees is vested on: (2012 Bar Question) a. The Secretary of Labor and Employment; b. The POEA Administrator; c. A and B concurrently; d. Neither of them.",
        "Answer": "b. The POEA Administrator [POEA Rules on Overseas land-based employment {2002}]."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 32,
        "Question": "What is the requirement in order that a compromise agreement involving labor standards cases be considered duly executed?",
        "Answer": "For a compromise agreement involving labor standards cases to be considered duly executed, such compromise agreement should be voluntarily agreed upon by the parties with the assistance of the Bureau of Labor Relations or the regional office of the Department of Labor and Employment. (Art. 227, Labor Code)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 33,
        "Question": "Lito Kuiangkuiang and Bong Urongsulong are employed as truck drivers of Line Movers. Inc. Usually. Lito is required by the personnel manager to just stay at the head office after office hours because he could be called to drive the trucks. While at the head office, Lito merely waits in the manager’s reception room. On the other hand, Bong is allowed to go home after office hours but is required to keep his cellular phone on so that he could be contacted whenever his services as driver becomes necessary. Would the hours that Lito and Bong are on call be considered compensable working hours?",
        "Answer": "The hours of Lito and Bong while on call can be considered compensable hours. The applicable rule is: An employee who is required to remain on call in the employer's premises or so close thereto that he cannot use the time effectively and gainfully for his own purpose shall be considered as working while on call. An employee who is not required to leave word at his home or with company officials where be may be reached is not working while on call. Here, Bong is required to stay at the office after office hours so he could be called to drive the trucks of the Company. As for Bong, he is required to keep his cellular phone so that he could be contacted whenever his services as driver as needed. Thus, the waiting time of Lito and Bong should be considered are compensable hours."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 34,
        "Question": "The following are excluded from the coverage of Title I, Book II of Labor Code of the Philippines (Conditions of Employment) except: (2012 Bar Question) a) Field personnel; b) Supervisors; c) Managers; d) Employees of government-owned and controlled corporations.",
        "Answer": "(b) Supervisors [Art. 82, Labor Code]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 35,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not compensable as hours worked? (2012 Bar Question) a. Travel away from home; b. Travel from home to work; c. Working while on call; d. Travel that is all in a day’s work.",
        "Answer": "a) Travel away from home. [Art. 84, Labor Code] b) Travel from home to work."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 36,
        "Question": "Percival was a mechanic of Pacific Airlines. He enjoyed a meal break of one hour. However, during meal breaks, he was required to be on stand-by for emergency work. During emergencies, he was made to forego his meals or to hurry up eating. He demanded payment of overtime for work done during his meal periods. Is Percival correct? Explain your answer.  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Percival is correct. Under Article 85 of the Labor Code and Book Ill, Rule I, Section 7 of the Rules, it shall be the duty of every employer to give his employees not less than sixty (60) minutes time-off for their regular meals. But where during the meal break, the workers are required to stand by for emergency work, such period is considered overtime (Pan American World Airways System (Phil.) v. Pan American Employees Association, G.R. No. L-16275, February 23, 1961, 1 SCRA 527)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 37,
        "Question": "Under what conditions may a compressed work week schedule be legally authorized as an exception to the eight-hour a day requirement under the Labor Code? (4%) State your answers and your reasons therefor. (2005 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "A compressed work week schedule may be authorized under the following conditions:"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 38,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Answer TRUE if the statement is true, or FALSE if the statement is false. Explain your answer in not more than two (2) sentences.  x x   [d] A waiver of the right to claim overtime pay is contrary to law. (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "True. As a general rule, overtime compensation cannot be waived, whether expressly or impliedly; and stipulation to the contrary is against the law. (Pampanga Sugar Dev. Co., Inc. v. CIR, 114 SCRA 725 .) An exception would be the adoption of a compressed work week on voluntary basis, subject to the guidelines of Department Order No. 02, Series of 2004."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 39,
        "Question": "Socorro is a clerk-typist in the Hospicio de San Jose, a charitable institution dependent for its existence on contributions and donations from well-wishers. She renders work eleven (11) hours a day but has not been given overtime pay since her place of work is a charitable institution. Is Socorro entitled to overtime pay? Explain briefly. ",
        "Answer": "Yes. Socorro is entitled to overtime compensation. She does not fall under any of the exceptions to the coverage of Art. 82, under the provisions of Hours of Work. The Labor Code is equally applicable to non-profit institutions. A covered employee who works beyond eight (8) hours is entitled to overtime compensation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 40,
        "Question": "Danilo Flores applied for the position of driver in the motorpool of Gold Company, a multinational corporation. Danilo was informed that he would frequently be working overtime as he would have to drive for the company's executives even beyond the ordinary eight-hour work day. He was provided with a contract of employment wherein he would be paid a monthly rate equivalent to 35 times his daily wage, regular sick and vacation leaves. 5 day-leave with pay every month and time off with pay when the company’s executives using the cars do not need Danilo’s service for more than eight hours a day, in lieu of overtime. Are the above provisions of the contract of employment in conformity with, or violative of, the law?",
        "Answer": "Except for the provision that Danilo shall have time off with pay when the company's executives using the cars do not need Danilo's service for more than eight hours a day, in lieu of overtime, the provisions of the contract of employment of Danilo are not violative of any labor law because they instead improve upon the present provisions of pertinent labor laws. Thus, the monthly rate equivalent to 35 times the daily wage may be sufficient to include overtime pay. There is no labor law requiring the payment of sick and vacation leaves except the provision for a five-day service incentive leave in the Labor Code. The 5-day-leave with pay every month has no counterpart in Labor Law and is very generous. As for the provision in Danilo's contract of employment that he shall receive time off with pay in lieu of overtime, this violates the provision of the Labor Code which states that undertime work on any particular day shall not be offset by overtime work on any other day. Permission given to the employer to go on leave on some other day of the week shall not exempt the employer from paying the additional compensation required by the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 41,
        "Question": "Pedro Sisid is a seaman who was employed in 1990 by Kuhol Ocean Transport. In May 1993, he was discharged and correspondingly paid vacation pay, terminal pay and overtime pay for the number of hours he actually rendered service in excess of his eight (8) working hours a day. Pedro Sisid, however, is dissatisfied with his overtime pay contending that he is on board the vessel 24 hours a day. or even beyond his eight (8) working hours which circumstance renders him on call whenever his service is needed. Therefore, he insists that he be paid 16 hours a day by way of overtime. Is the contention of seaman Pedro Sisid tenable? Why?",
        "Answer": "No. The contention of seaman Sisid is not tenable. The fact that he is on board the vessel 24 hours a day does not mean that beyond his eight working hours, he could be also considered as working because he is on call, and thus, is entitled to overtime pay. Because he is a seaman, this circumstance means he is on board his vessel while at sea. But he is not thereby on call as to be entitled to overtime pay because when it is not his working time, he can, if he chooses to do so, use said non-working time effectively and gainfully for his own purpose. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: No, there being a record of actual overtime services rendered. An estimated period of overtime is valid as a basis for payment of overtime, only in a case where overtime services are actually being rendered regularly but no record of the hours were kept."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 42,
        "Question": "A manufacturing company operates on a 6-day workweek. It employs 200 workers whose regular workday is 8 hours. On May 1. 1990, the company and Union M, the employees; bargaining agent, agreed that the workday be 7 hours from Monday to Wednesday and 9 hours from Thursday to Saturday. The agreement was ratified by all the employees. In 1991 Union M lost its majority status and Union P was certified as bargaining representative. Union P filed a claim against the Company for unpaid overtime pay of the 200 employees from May 1. 1990 when they started working 9 hours per day, 3 days a week. Invoking the 1990 agreement, the Company moved to dismiss the claim of Union P. Decide with reasons.",
        "Answer": "The claim of Union P is valid. The Labor Code is very clear: Undertime work on any particular day shall not be offset by overtime work on any other day. (Article 88, Labor Code) The right arising from the above provision, meaning, entitlement to overtime pay for one hour for working 9 hours per day, 3 days a week. (Article 87, Labor Code) cannot be considered as waived by a CBA even if the CBA is ratified by the employees concerned. The waiver in this instance is against the law, morals, and public policy. The law must prevail over the CBA."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 43,
        "Question": "Ping Gabo is the Chief Engineer of the National Publishing Corp. with a monthly salary of P3.000.00. He works over eight (8) hours daily from Monday to Saturday. In May. June and July 1991, he rendered, each month, ten (10) hours beyond his regular work schedule. Is he entitled to overtime pay and holiday pay? Why?",
        "Answer": "The entitlement of Gabo to overtime pay and holiday pay is dependent on whether he is a managerial employee or not. If he Is a managerial employee, he is not entitled to overtime pay and holiday pay. The Labor Code provides that the provisions that grant overtime pay and holiday pay shall not apply, among others, to managerial employees. A managerial employee is defined by the Code as referring to those whose primaiy duty consists of the management of the establishment in which they are employed or of a department or subdivision thereof, and to other officers or members of the managerial staff. Gabo, as Chief Engineer, appears to be a managerial employee. On the other hand, his monthly pay is rather low for a managerial employee. Despite his title, his duty may not consist of a management of department or of a subdivision thereof."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 44,
        "Question": "After working from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. on a Thursday as one of 5,000 employees in a beer factory, A hurried home to catch the early evening news and have dinner with his family. At around 10 p.m. of the same day, the plant manager called and ordered A to fill in for C who missed the second shift. A. May A validly refuse the plant manager’s directive? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "YES. A may validly refuse to fill in for C. A may not be compelled to perform overtime work considering that the plant manager’s directive is not for an emergency overtime work, as contemplated under Article 89 of the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 45,
        "Question": "Assuming that A was made to work from 11 p.m. on Thursday until 2 a.m. on Friday, may the company argue that, since he was two hours late in coming to work on Thursday morning, he should only be paid for work rendered from 1 a.m. to 2 a.m.? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "NO. Undertime is not off-set by overtime (Art. 88, Labor Code)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 46,
        "Question": "The Overseas Construction Company, a domestic corporation with a recruitment license, hired two thousand Filipino workers and assigned them to its construction project in Kuwait. They were given free housing, work clothing and food. The master employment contract approved for them by the Philippine Overseas Employment Administration (POEA) stipulated that they were to work at the overseas jobsite for twelve (12) hours per day and that they were accordingly to be paid wages higher than the POEA-approved schedule of pay rates. The individual employment contracts also contained the same stipulations. And during the pre-departure briefings at the company’s Mandaluyong plant site, the workers were told about these stipulations. By actual compu-tation, the wages paid at the overseas jobsite were at least twenty-five percent (25%) more than the POEA-approved rates. Moreover, the record shows that the workers did not always render the full twelve (12) hours of work stipulated in the employment contract. Back home after completing their one-year overseas assignment, the workers engaged your services as their lawyer to prosecute a complaint with the POEA for recovery of unpaid overtime work. What would your advice be?",
        "Answer": "Before I give an advise, I will first find the answer to this basic question: Were the workers actually paid for their overtime work when they received wages that were at least twenty-five percent (25%) more than the POEA-approved rates? The answer is No if the 25% added to the POEA- approved rate (which we assume is a rate for a day of eight (8) hours work) is only 25% of such POEA-approved daily wage rate. This is because what should be paid to the workers for the four (4) hours that they work overtime in their twelve (12) hour day (a 12-hour work day is 4 hours in excess of an 8-hour work day) should be 50% more of such POEA- approved rate. The four (4) hours of work is 50% of the normal weight (8) hours of work a day plus 25% of such additional 50% for purposes of paying the overtime rate. There is also the night differential pay to take into account because a 12-hour shift will include working hours from 10:00 p.m. to 6:00 a.m. If the higher-than-the POEA- approved rate is computed as indicated above, I will advise the workers not to sue for they have already been paid for their overtime work. If the higher-than-the-POEA-approved rates is not, however, computed as indicated above, the fact that the POEA-approved the contracts and that the workers agreed to the rates they receive will not be a bar to a complaint for unpaid overtime pay, the right to which cannot be waived. ANOTHER SUGGESTED ANSWER: The rate approved by the POEA has built-in overtime pay. Thus, there is no basis for the claim for overtime pay."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 47,
        "Question": "Work may be performed beyond eight (8) hours a day provided that: (2012 Bar Question) a) Employee is paid for overtime work an additional compensation equivalent to his regular wage plus at least 30% thereof; b) Employee is paid for overtime work an additional compensation equivalent to his regular wage plus at least 30% thereof; c) Employee is paid for overtime work an additional compensation equivalent to his regular wage plus at least 20% thereof; d) None of the above.",
        "Answer": "(a) Employee is paid for overtime work an additional compensation equivalent to his regular wage plus at least (25% thereof. [Art. 87, Labor Code]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 48,
        "Question": "The provisions of the Labor Code on the Working Conditions and Rest Periods of employees are inapplicable to the following employees, except: (2012 Bar Question) a. A supervisor in a fast food chain; b. A family driver; c. A laborer without any fixed salary, but receiving a compensation depending upon the result of his work; d. A contractual employee.",
        "Answer": "d. A contractual employee."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 49,
        "Question": "May the employer and employee stipulate that the latter’s regular or basic salary already includes the overtime pay, such that when the employee actually works overtime he cannot claim overtime pay? (2012 Bar Question) a) Yes, provided there is a clear written agreement knowingly and freely entered into by the employee; b) Yes, provided the mathematical result shows that agreed legal wage rate and the overtime pay. Computed separately, are equal to or higher than the separate amounts legally due; c) No, the employer and employee cannot stipulate that the latter’s regular or basic salary already includes the overtime pay; d) A and B",
        "Answer": "c) No, the employer and employee cannot stipulate that the latter’s regular or basic salary includes the overtime pay. [Art. 87, Labor Code]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 50,
        "Question": "LKG Garments Inc. makes baby clothes for export. As part of its measures to meet its orders, LKG requires its employees to work beyond eight (8) hours everyday, from Monday to Saturday. It pays its employees an additional 35% of their regular hourly wage for work rendered in excess of eight (8) hours per day. Because of additional orders, LKG now requires two (2) shifts of workers with both shifts working beyond eight (8) hours but only up to a maximum of four (4) hours. Carding is an employee who used to render up to six (6) hours of overtime work before the change in schedule. He complains that the change adversely affected him because now he can only earn up to a maximum of four (4) hours worth of overtime pay. Does Carding have a cause of action against the company? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "NO. A change in work schedule is a management prerogative of LKG. Thus, Carding has no cause of action against LKG if, as a result of its change to two (2) shifts, he now can only expect a maximum of four (4) hours overtime work. Besides, Art. 97 of the Labor Code does not guarantee Carding a certain number of hours of overtime work. In Manila Jockey Employees’ Union v. Manila Jockey Club (517 SCRA 707), the Supreme Court held that the basis of overtime claim is an employee’s having been 'permitted to work'. Otherwise, as in this case, such is not demandable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 51,
        "Question": "As a tireman in a gasoline station, open twenty four (24) hours a day 'with only five (5) employees, Goma worked from 10:00 P.M. until 7:00 A.M. of the following day. He claims he is entitled to night shift differential. Is he correct? Explain briefly. ",
        "Answer": "Yes. Under Art. 86 of the Labor Code, night shift differential shall be paid to every employee for work performed between 10:00 o’clock in the evening to six o’clock in the morning. Therefore, Goma Is entitled to night shift differential for work performed from 10:00 pm until 6:00 am of the day following, but not from 6:00 am to 7:00 am of the same day. The Omnibus Rules Implementing the Labor Code (In Book ill, Rule lI dealing with night shift differential) provides that its provisions on night shift differential shall NOT apply to employees of 'retail and service establishments regularly employing not more than five (5) workers'. Because of this provision, Goma is not entitled to night shift differential because the gasoline station where he works has only five employees."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 52,
        "Question": "Republic Drug Co. has 1,000 employees, including 50 managerial personnel, 90 supervisors and 150 sale representatives. The regular workday in the Company is from 8:00 a.m. to 5:00 p.m. The sales representatives register their presence with the timekeeper at 8:00 A.M. every day before they go to their respective sales territories. They are paid a basic salary plus commission. Sixty of the sales representatives are members of the Republic Salesmen Union which sent to the Company a set of bargaining proposals, including a demand for payment of overtime pay of the sales representatives for working beyond 5:00 P.M. everyday. The Company refused to consider the bargaining proposals and rejected the demand for overtime pay for the reason that the sales representatives are not entitled thereto. The Union filed an unfair labor practice case against the Company for refusal to bargain, and after complying with the legal requirements declared a strike. a) Was the Company legally justified in rejecting the Union’s demand for overtime pay? Reason.",
        "Answer": "The Company was legally justified. Under the Labor Code, (in Article 82). 'field personnel are among those classes of workers who are not entitled to overtime pay, and the phrase 'field personnel' includes sales representatives who. like other field personnel, are non- agricultural employee who regularly perform their duties away from the principal place of business or branch office of the employer and whose actual hours of work in the field cannot be determined with reasonable certainty."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 53,
        "Question": "A wage order may be reviewed on appeal by the National Wages and Productivity Commission under these grounds, except: (2012 Bar Question) a. Grave abuse of discretion; b. Non-conformity with prescribed procedure; c. Questions of law; d. Gross under or over-valuation.",
        "Answer": "d) Gross under or over-valuation"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 54,
        "Question": "The following are exempt from the rules on minimum wages, except: (2012 Bar Question) a. Household or domestic helpers; b. Homeworkers engaged in needle work; c. Workers’ in duly registered establishment in the cottage industry; d. Workers in the duly registered cooperative.",
        "Answer": "b) Workers in the duly registered cooperative. [Sec. 3 (d), Rule VII, Book III of Omnibus Rules requires recommendations of Bureau of Cooperative Development and approval of DOLE Secretary – matters that are not in the suggested answer]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 55,
        "Question": "Benito is the owner of an eponymous clothing brand that is a top seller. He employs a number of male and female models who wear Benito's clothes in promotional shoots and videos. His deal with the models is that Benito will pay them with 3 sets of free clothes per week. Is this arrangement allowed? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. the arrangement is not allowed. The models are Benito’s employees. As such, their services require compensation in legal tender (Art. 102, Labor Code). The three sets of clothes, regardless of value, are in kind; hence, the former’s compensation is not in the form prescribed by law. ANOTHER SUGGESTED ANSWER: Under Article 102 of the Labor Code, wages of an employee are to be paid only in legal tender, even when expressly requested bv the employee. Hence, no lawful deal in this regard can be entered into by and between Benito and his models. SUGGESTED ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: The models are not employees. Therefore, Art. 102 of the Labor Code applies. The payment does not have to be in legal tender. But even if they are employees, the wage arrangement between Benito and the models is allowed by Art. 97(f) of the Labor Code which defines wage as the remuneration or earning paid to an employee, however designated, capable of being expressed in terms of money, whether fixed or ascertained on a time, task, piece, or commission basis, or other method of calculating the same, which is payable by an employer to an employee under a written or unwritten contract of employment for work done or to be done, or for services rendered or to be rendered. It includes the fair and reasonable value, as determined by the Secretary of Labor, of board, lodging or other facilities customarily furnished by the employer to the employee."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 56,
        "Question": "Tarcisio was employed as operations manager and received a monthly salary of ₱25,000.00 through his payroll account with DB Bank. He obtained a loan from Roberto to purchase a car. Tarcisio failed to pay Roberto when the loan fell due. Roberto sued to collect, and moved to garnish Tarcisio's payroll account. The latter vigorously objected and argued that salaries were exempt from garnishment. Is Tarcisio correct? Explain your answer.  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The term 'wages applies to compensation for manual labor, skilled or unskilled, while salary denotes a compensation for a higher degree of employment. (Goa vs. Court of Appeals. 140 SCRA 304). Under Article 1708 of the Civil Code, only 'wages are exempt from attachment or execution. Salaries are not exempt from attachment or execution. (Goa vs. Court of Appeals, 140 SCRA 304)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 57,
        "Question": "1) Distinguish 'salary from 'wages. 2) Are these subject to attachment and execution?",
        "Answer": "The term 'wages applies to compensation for manual labor, skilled or unskilled, while salary denotes a compensation for a higher degree of employment. (Goa vs. Court of Appeals. 140 SCRA 304). ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: 1) 'Wages are those paid to any employee as his remuneration or earnings payable by an employer for work done or to be done, or for services rendered or to be rendered. On the other hand, 'salary is used in the law that provides for a 13th-month pay. In this law, basic salary includes all remuneration or earnings paid by an employer to his employees for services rendered, but does not include allowances or monetary benefits which are not considered or integrated as part of the regular or basic salary. (Art. 97(f). Labor Code; Sec. 2(b), P.D. No. 851) 2) Under Article 1708 of the Civil Code, only 'wages are exempt from attachment or execution. Salaries are not exempt from attachment or execution. (Goa vs. Court of Appeals, 140 SCRA 304)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 58,
        "Question": "How much attorney's fees may a lawyer assess a culpable party in cases of unlawful withholding of wages?",
        "Answer": "In cases of unlawful withholding of wages, the culpable party may be assessed attorney's fees equivalent to ten percent (10%) of the amount of wages recovered. (Art. III, Labor Code)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 59,
        "Question": "The Regional Tripartite Wages and Productivity Board (RTWPB) for Region 3 issued a wage order on November 2, 2017 fixing the minimum wages for all industries throughout Region 3. (a) Is the wage order subject to the approval of the National Wages and Productivity Commission before it takes effect? ",
        "Answer": "No, because the NWPC exercises only technical and administrative supervision -over the RTWPB (Article 121 (g), Labor Code). ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: No, the Wage Order becomes effective fifteen (15) days after its publication in at least one (l) newspaper of general circulation in the region pursuant to the Rules of Procedure in Minimum Wage Fixing."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 60,
        "Question": "what circumstances may the Kilusang Walang Takot, a federation of labor organizations that publicly and openly assails the wage order as blatantly unjust, initiate the review of the wage increases under the wage order without waiting for the end of the 12-month period? Explain your answer.  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The federation may initiate a review of the • wage order even before the expiration of the 12-month period when there are supervening conditions, such as extraordinary increase in prices of petroleum products and basic goods/services which demand a review of minimum wage rates as determined by the Board and confirmed by the Commission."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 61,
        "Question": "A lady worker was born with a physical deformity, specifically, hard of hearing, speech impaired and color blind. However, these deficiencies do not impair her working ability. Can the employer classify the lady worker as a handicapped worker so that her daily wage will only be seventy-five percent (75%) of the applicable daily minimum wage? [5%]",
        "Answer": "No, the employer cannot classify the lady worker as a handicapped worker because according to the facts in the question, her deficiencies do not impair her working ability. If her earning capacity is therefore not also impaired, then she cannot be considered a handicapped worker. Because of the above fact, the employer shall not pay her less than the applicable daily minimum wage. (See Article 78 of the Labor Code)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 62,
        "Question": "The SFH President asks you, being the hospital's counsel, which of these two (2) options is the legal and proper way of terminating Amaya: a) terminate her for a just cause under Article 288 of the Labor Code (Termination by Employer); or b) terminate her for violating her probationary contract. Explain. (2016)",
        "Answer": "I will advise the President of SFH to terminate Amaya for violating her probationary contract. Part and parcel of the standards of her employment is to strictly follow the Code of Conduct of SFH. The act of defaming Dr. Ligaya is certainly a misdemeanor that is usually not acceptable in any work environment. With such attitude Amaya displayed, she cannot pass the company standard of SFH. Termination made for reasons provided under Article 296 of the Labor Code before the expiration of the six-month probationary period is well within the employer's rights to sever the employer-employee relationship."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 63,
        "Question": "On January 3, 1988, Sea Breeze Restaurant, Inc. (SBRI) hired Juan Reyes as a probationary kitchen helper. He received and cleaned food ingredients delivered by suppliers and stored them in freezers, cleaned kitchenware and utensils, and kept the kitchen tidy. On July 1, 1988, he was sent to the company’s doctor for a complete medical examination. Thereafter, he continued working. On July 8, 1988, the doctor submitted his report finding Juan to have minimal pulmonary tuberculosis (TB). The manager consults you as the labor adviser of the company, and asks if Juan’s employment can be terminated as his presence was a hazard to the health of other workers and customers of the restaurant. (a) Within the time frame of the problem, was there any change in Juan’s employment status? (b) When did the change occur? (c) Why did it occur? (d) Can the company still terminate Juan as a probationer? (e) Under what conditions may Juan be terminated considering his health? Explain. (f) Based on your analysis of the factual and legal situation, what course of action would you advise the company to take?",
        "Answer": "(a) There was a change in the employment status of Juan, from probationary to regular employment. (b) July 4, 1988, after his six-month probationary period. (c) The Labor Code (Art. 281) provides that 'an employee who is allowed to work after a probationary period shall be considered a regular employee. (d) No, Juan cannot be terminated as a probationer because he is already a regular employee. (e) Under Article 284, Juan can only be terminated if he is found to be suffering from a disease, Minimal PTB, which is prejudicial to his health as well as to the health of his co-employees, and said disease cannot be cured within a period of six (6) months even with proper medical treatment. (f) I will advise the company to give Juan a formal notice that his termination is being contemplated. Give him an opportunity to defend himself. Inform him that the termination will be effective after he is given a separation pay equivalent to one month salary for every year of service."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 64,
        "Question": "Mr. X was hired by Y Company on probation for six months as general utility worker. On the expiration of the probationary period, Mr. X was informed by Y Co. that his work was unsatisfactory and failed to meet the required standard. To give him a chance to improve his performance, Y Co. instead of terminating Mr. X’s services, extended, with X’s written consent, the probation period for another three months. This extension notwithstanding, his performance did not improve, on account of which, Y Co. terminated Mr. X's services at the end of the extended period. Mr. X filed a case for illegal dismissal contending that he was already regular at the time of his dismissal pursuant to Art. 281 of the Labor Code, the particular portion of which provides: 'xxx. An employee who is allowed to work after a probationary period shall be considered a regular employee. Therefore, he could not have been lawfully dismissed for failure to meet company standards as a probationary worker. Decide with reason.",
        "Answer": "Mr. X could not argue that because his probationary period was extended beyond six months he was now a regular employee and thus could no longer be terminated except for Just cause or when authorized by law. The fact is that the probationary period of Mr. X was extended beyond six months with his consent. It was to give him an opportunity to improve his performance. Thus, it was legal for Y Company to terminate Mr. X for his failure to meet company standard as a probationary worker. The Labor Code provides that probationary employment shall not exceed six (6) months. But the Supreme Court has ruled that said probationary period could be extended with the consent of the probationary employee lo give him an opportunity to improve his performance (Art. 281. Labor Code)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 65,
        "Question": "Aleta Quiros was a faculty member at BM Institute, a private educational institution. She was hired on a year-to-year basis under the probationary employment period provision of the Manual of Regulations for Private Schools. The terms and conditions of her engagement were defined under her renewable yearly contract. For reasons of its own, BM Institute no longer wanted to continue with Aleta's teaching services. Thus, after the contract for her second year expired, BM Institute advised Aleta that her contract would no longer be renewed. This advice prompted Aleta to file a complaint for illegal dismissal against BM Institute. Will the complaint prosper? (2013 Bar Questions) (A) Yes, because no just or authorized cause existed for the termination of her probationary employment. (B) Yes, because under the Labor Code, Aleta became a regular employee after 6 months and she may now only be dismissed for cause. (C) No, because there was no dismissal to speak of. Her employment was automatically terminated upon the expiration of her year-to-year fixed term employment. (D) No, because BM Institute may dismiss its faculty members at will in the exercise of its academic freedom. (E) No, because Aleta was still on probationary employment.",
        "Answer": "(A) Yes, because no just or authorized cause existed for the termination of her probationary employment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 66,
        "Question": "A was hired in a sugar plantation performing such tasks as weeding, cutting and loading canes, planting cane points, fertilizing and cleaning the drainage. Because his daily presence in the field was not required, A also worked as a houseboy at the house of the plantation owner. For the next planting season, the owner decided not to hire A as a plantation worker but as a houseboy instead. Furious, A filed a case for illegal dismissal against the plantation owner. Decide with reason.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "A is a regular seasonal employee. Therefore, he cannot be dismissed without just or valid cause. The primary standard for determining regular employment is the reasonable connection between the particular activity performed by the employee in relation to the usual trade or business of the employer. Converting A to a mere houseboy at the house of the plantation owner amounts to an act of severing his employment relations as its plantation worker."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 67,
        "Question": "Julius Lagat, a truck driver, was hired by Merdeka Trucking Company which is engaged in the business of hauling farm produce, fertilizer and other cargo for an agribusiness company on a non-seasonal and continuing basis. Lagat’s contract stipulated that it was effective for six months from date of execution, renewable for the same period. Upon expiration of the renewed contract. Lagat was advised by Merdeka that his services were terminated. Lagat filed a complaint for illegal dismissal against Merdeka which contended that Lagat had no cause of action as his employment was for a definite and specific period. You are the Labor Arbiter. Decide with reasons.",
        "Answer": "As Labor Arbiter, I will decide in favor of Lagat. From the circumstances of the case, it is apparent, that the six month period was imposed to preclude the employee from acquiring security of tenure. The contract that Merdeka had with Lagat can be considered as circumventing the law that gives to a worker the right to security of tenure, considering that Lagat was a truck driver in a business that was not seasonal and was on a continuing basis. Since Lagat’s contract was a renewed contract, at the very least, he worked beyond the probationary period, making him a regular employee and clearly entitled to security of tenure."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 68,
        "Question": "Borloloy & Co. is engaged in the construction business which hired the services of Ispongklong as mason and Agaton as carpenter in 1977. Every time their services are needed, Ispongklong and Agaton are issued notices of employment by Borloloy & Co. in the following tenor: 'This is to inform you that you have been hired at Lahar Bldg., as mason and carpenter respectively at a monthly salary/daily or hourly of PI2.40. Your employment shall be deemed automatically terminated either at the completion of the project or upon the completion of the work requiring your respective services to start May 12, 1977. ACCEPTED: Such an arrangement continued wherein both Agaton and Ispongklong became members of a work pool from where Borloloy & Co. draws manpower to work on various projects. After each project they have been assigned to is completed, Borloloy & Co. reported the names of Ispongklong and Agaton to the Social Security System for registration. In 1987 (or after ten years of service) they received a notice from Borloloy & Co. informing them that their services are no longer needed. Ispongklong and Agaton immediately filed a case for illegal dismissal alleging that they are regular and permanent workers of Borloloy & Co. having worked for it for ten (10) years hence prayed for reinstatement and back wages. Borloloy & Co. on the other hand, claims that Agaton and Ispongklong are project employees whereby their employment is automatically terminated either at the completion of the phase of work requiring their respective service as stated in their respective Notice of Employment the sample test of which is quoted above. If you are the Labor Arbiter assigned to the case, how will you decide the controversy?",
        "Answer": "As Labor Arbiter, I will promulgate a decision finding the dismissal of Agaton and Ispongklong illegal. Ispongklong and Agaton ceased to be project employees when they became members of a work pool from where their employer draws manpower to work on various projects. Thus, as regular employees, they can be terminated only if there is just cause or when otherwise authorized by law (Art. 280, Labor Code)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 69,
        "Question": "Damian wants to know if he was unlawfully terminated. Explain. (1988 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Damian was unlawfully terminated. There could be just cause for his termination if his dishonesty and/or fraud are established, but there is no showing that the twin requirements of notice and hearing were observed by the company, hence the dismissal is illegal."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 70,
        "Question": "Damian asks you if he had been given all his terminal entitlements.",
        "Answer": "If there is no just cause for the termination of Damian, he has the right to reinstatement without loss of seniority rights and to his backwages computed from the time his compensation was withheld from him up to the time of his reinstatement (Art. 279)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 71,
        "Question": "The workers worked as cargadors at the warehouse and ricemills of farm A for several years. As cargadors, they loaded, unloaded and piled sacks of rice from the warehouse to the cargo trucks for delivery to different places. They were paid by Farm A on a piece-rate basis. Are the workers considered regular employee? (2012 Bar Question) a) Yes, because Farm A paid wages directly to these workers without the intervention of any third party independent contractor; b) Yes, their work is directly related, necessary and vital to the operations of the farm; c) No, because Farm A did not have the power to control the workers with respect to the means and methods by which the work is to be accomplished; d) A and B",
        "Answer": "d) A and B."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 72,
        "Question": "Mr. Ortanez has been in the building construction business for several years. He asks you, as his new labor counsel, for the rules he must observe in considering regular employment in the construction industry. You clarify that an employee, project or non-project, will acquire regular status if __________. (2013 Bar Questions) (A) he has been continuously employed for more than one year (B) his contract of employment has been repeatedly renewed, from project to project, for several years (C) he performs work necessary and desirable to the business, without a fixed period and without reference to any specific project or undertaking (D) he has lived up to the company's regularization standards (E) All of the above.",
        "Answer": "(C) he performs work necessary and desirable to the business, without a fixed period and without reference to any specific project or undertaking."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 73,
        "Question": "Don Don is hired as a contractual employee of CALLHELP, a call center. His contract is expressly for a term of 4 months. Don Don is hired for 3 straight contracts of 4 months each but at 2-week intervals between contracts. After the third contract ended, Don Don is told that he will no longer be given another contract because of poor performance. Don Don files a suit for regularization and for illegal dismissal, claiming that he is a regular employee of CALLHELP and that he was dismissed without cause. You are the Labor Arbiter. How would you decide the case? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "As Labor Arbiter, I will decide the case in favor of Don Don. Given the nature of Don Don’s work, which consist of activities usually or desirable in the usual business of CALLHELP, Don Don should be considered a regular employee. CALLHELP’s termination of Don Don’s service in the guise of 'poor performance' is not valid. Whether for a probationary or regular employee, the requisites of dismissal on that ground do not appear to have been complied with by the employer here."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 74,
        "Question": "Under the Labor Code on Working Conditions and Rest Periods, a person hired by a high company official but paid for by the company to clean and maintain his staff house is regarded as (2011 BAR) (A) a person rendering personal service to another. (B) a regular company employee. (C) a family member. (D) domestic helper.",
        "Answer": "(B) a regular company employee."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 75,
        "Question": "Albert and four others signed employment contracts with Reign Publishers from January 1 to March 31, 2011 to help clear up encoding backlogs. By first week of April 2011, however, they remained at work. On June 30 Reign’s manager notified them that their work would end that day. Do they have valid reason to complain? (2011 BAR) (A) No, since fixed term employment, to which they agreed, is allowed. (B) Yes, their job was necessary and desirable to the employer’s business and, therefore, they are regular employees. (C) Yes, when they worked beyond March without an extended fixed term employment contract, they became regular employees. (D) No, since the 3-month extension is allowed in such employment.",
        "Answer": "(C) Yes, when they worked beyond March without an extended fixed term employment contract, they became regular employees."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 76,
        "Question": "Mario Brothers, plumbing works contractor, entered into an agreement with Axis Business Corporation (Axis) for the plumbing works of its building under construction. Mario Brothers engaged the services of Tristan, Arthur, and Jojo as plumber, pipe fitter, and threader, respectively. These workers have worked for Mario Brothers in various projects spanning five years. Mario Brothers claims the 3 workers are project employees. It explains that the agreement is, if the works contract is cancelled due to the fault of the client, the period of employment is automatically terminated. Is the contractor correct? Explain. (2016)",
        "Answer": "No. In GMA Network, Inc v. Pabriga, it was ruled that the repeated hiring of project employees to perform tasks which are necessary and desirable in the usual business or trade of the employer is sufficient evidence of the necessity, if not indispensability, of the workers’ service to the employer’s business."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 77,
        "Question": "Distinguish the project employees from regular employees. (1996 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "A regular employee is one engaged to perform activities which are usually necessary or desirable in the usual business or trade of the employer. On the other hand, a project employee is one whose employment is fixed for a specific project or undertaking the completion or termination of which has been determined at the time of the engagement of the employee (See Art. 280 of the Labor Code)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 78,
        "Question": "How is a project worker different from a casual or contractual worker? Briefly explain your answers, (6% )",
        "Answer": "A **project worker** is employed for a specific project or undertaking the completion or termination of which is determined at the time of his engagement. His work need not be incidental to the business of the employer. His employment may exceed 1 year without necessarily making him a regular employee. A **casual employee** is engaged to perform a job, work, or service which is incidental to the business of the employer; moreover, the definite period of his employment is made known to him at the time of his engagement. His continued employment after the lapse of one year makes him a regular employee. A project worker, on the other hand, is a specific term used to designate workers in the construction industry hired to perform a specific undertaking for a fixed period which is co-terminus with a project or phase thereof determined at the time of the engagement of the employee. There is no such requirement for an ordinary contractual worker."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 79,
        "Question": "Design Consultants, Inc. was engaged by the PNCC to supervise the construction of the South Expressway Extension. Design Consultants, Inc. hired Omar as a driver for two (2) years. After his two-year contract expired, he was extended another contract for nine (9) months. These contracts were entered into during the various stages and before the completion of the extension project. Omar claims that because of these repeated contracts, he is now a regular employee of Design Consultants, Inc. Is he correct? Explain briefly. ",
        "Answer": "Yes. The principal test for determining whether a particular employee is a 'project employee' as distinguished from a 'regular employee' is whether or not the 'project employee' was assigned to carry out a 'specific project or undertaking,' the duration and scope of which were specified at the time the employee was engaged for the projects. In the problem given, there is no showing that Omar was informed that he was to be assigned to a 'specific project or undertaking'. Neither has it been established that he was informed of the duration and scope of such project or undertaking at the time of his engagement. Moreover, the re-hiring of Omar is sufficient evidence of the necessity or the indispensability of his services to the company’s business. Hence, Omar is correct in claiming that he is a regular employee of Design Consultants, Inc.."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 80,
        "Question": "Aldrich Zamora, a welder, was hired on February 1972 by Asian Contractors Corporation (ACC) for a project. He was made to sign a contract stipulating that his services were being hired for the completion of the project, but not later than December 30, 1972, whichever comes first. After December 1972, Zamora, being a man of many talents, was hired for different projects of ACC in various capacities, such as carpenter, electrician and plumber. In all of these engagements. Zamora signed a contract similar to his first contract except for the estimated completion dates of the project for which he was hired. What is Zamora's status with ACC? is he a contract worker, a project employee, a temporary or a regular employee? State your reason.",
        "Answer": "Zamora is a **regular employee**. He was engaged to work in various projects of ACC for a considerable length of time, on an activity that is usually necessary desirable in the usual business or trade of ACC. The provisions of written agreement to the contrary notwithstanding, an employment shall be deemed to be regular where the employee has been engaged to perform activities which are usually necessary or desirable in the usual business or trade of the employer."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 81,
        "Question": "Martillo and other similarly-situated project workers demanded that the increases be extended to them, inasmuch as they should now be considered regular employees and members of the bargaining unit. (2006 Bar Question) If you were ABC's legal counsel, how would you respond to this demand?",
        "Answer": "As legal counsel for ABC, I would argue that the employment of Martillo was fixed for a specific project or undertaking, the completion or termination of which has been determined at the time of his engagement. Rendering 14 months of work does not make him a regular employee, when to begin with, he was employed for a specific project. The rule on more than 1 year of service making the employment regular applies only to casual employees, hence, Mariano does not belong to the bargaining unit of regular employees."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 82,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Answer TRUE if the statement is true, or FALSE if the statement is false. Explain your answer in not more than two (2) sentences.  Seafarers who have worked for twenty (20) years on board the same vessel are regular employees. (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "FALSE. Seafarers as overseas Filipino workers are fixed-term employees whose continued rehiring should not be interpreted as a basis for regularization but rather as a series of contract renewals sanctioned under the doctrine set by Millares vs. NLRC (Gu-Miro v. Adorable, 437 SCRA 162 )."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 83,
        "Question": "Lucy was one of approximately 500 call center agents at Hambergis, Inc. She was hired as a contractual employee four years ago. Her contracts would be for a duration of five (5) months at a time, usually after a one-month interval. Her re-hiring was contingent on her performance for the immediately preceding contract. Six (6) months after the expiration of her last contract, Lucy went to Hambergis personnel department to inquire why she was not yet being recalled to work. She was told that her performance during her last contract was 'below average.' Lucy seeks your legal advice about her chances of getting her job back. What will your advice be? (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will advise Lucy that she can get her job back if she files a case for illegal dismissal. In this case, Lucy is a regular employee because the employment contracts of five (5) months at a time, for four (4) years are obviously intended to circumvent an employee's security of tenure, and are therefore void. As a regular employee, Lucy may only be dismissed from service based on just and authorized causes enumerated under the Labor Code, and after observance of procedural due process prescribed under said law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 84,
        "Question": "The labor sector has been loudly agitating for the end of labor-only contracting, as distinguished from job contracting. Explain these two kinds of labor contracting, and give the effect of a finding that one is a labor-only contractor. Explain your answers. (4%) (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "There is **labor-only contracting** where: (1) the person supplying workers to an employer does not have substantial capital or investment in the form of tools, equipment, machineries, work premises, among others; and (2) the workers recruited and placed by such person are performing activities which are directly related to the principal business of such employer. **Job contracting** refers to an arrangement where a legitimate independent contractor undertakes to perform a job, work, or service on its own responsibility, according to its own manner and method, and free from control and direction of the principal, except as to the results. If found to be a labor-only contractor, the person or intermediary shall be considered merely as an agent of the employer, who shall be responsible to the workers in the same manner and extent as if the latter were directly employed by him."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 85,
        "Question": "Are the TMRs employees of Empire? (2016)",
        "Answer": "Yes. From the time Empire contracted the services of Style, both engaged in labor-only contracting. Where the contractor or subcontractor does not have substantial capital or investment in the form of tools, equipment, machineries, work premises, etc., there is labor-only contracting. Consequently, Empire is deemed the direct employer of the TMRs."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 86,
        "Question": "Were the TMRs illegally dismissed by Wave?",
        "Answer": "No. As the TMRs are employees of Empire, Wave did not have the power of dismissal; thus, even if Wave dismissed the TMRs the same has no consequence."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 87,
        "Question": "Distinguish Labor-Only contracting and Job-Only contracting.  (2012 BAR)",
        "Answer": "Job-Only Contracting is where the contractor has substantial capital or investment, carries on an independent business, and undertakes to perform the job, work or service on its own responsibility, according to its own manner and method, and free from control and direction of the principal in all matters connected with the performance of the work except as to the results thereof. Labor-Only Contracting is prohibited while Job Contracting is allowed by law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 88,
        "Question": "K is a legitimate contractor hired by G for six (6) months. On the third month, G remitted to K the salaries and wages of the employees. However, K absconded with the money leaving the employees unpaid. The disgruntled employees demanded from G the payment of their salaries. Is G liable? (2012 Bar Question) a. No, because G has already remitted the employees’ salaries to K, validly excusing G from liability. b. Yes, because he is jointly and solidarily liable for whatever monetary claims the employees may have against K; c. Yes, because of the principle of 'a fair day’s wage for a fair day’s work'; d. B and C.",
        "Answer": "b. Yes, because he is jointly and solidarily liable for whatever monetary claims the employees may have against K;."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 89,
        "Question": "In legitimate contracting, the law requires that the following rights must be observed, except: (2012 Bar Question) a. The contract calls for the performance of a specific job, work or service; b. It is stipulated that the performance of a specific job, work or service must be within a definite predetermined period; c. The performance of a specific job, work or service has to completed either within or outside the premises of the principal; d. The principal has control over the performance of a specific job, work or service.",
        "Answer": "d. The principal has control over the performance of a specific job, work or service."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 90,
        "Question": "Linis Manpower, Inc. (LMI) had provided janitorial services to the Philippine Overseas Employment Administration (POEA) since March 2009. Its service contract was renewed every three months. However, in the bidding held in June 2012, LMI was disqualified and excluded. In 2013, six janitors of LMI formerly assigned at POEA filed a complaint for underpayment of wages. Both LMI and POEA were impleaded as respondents. Should POEA, a government agency subject to budgetary appropriations from Congress, be held liable solidarily with LMI for the payment of salary differentials due to the complainant? Cite the legal basis of your answer. (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes, but only to the extent of work performed under the contract. Article 106 of the Labor Code provides that if the contractor or subcontractor fails to pay the wages of his employees... the employer shall be jointly and severally liable with his contractor or subcontractor to such employees to the extent of the work performed under the contract. The fact that POEA is a government agency is of no moment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 91,
        "Question": "Luningning Foods engaged the services of Lamitan Manpower, Inc., a bona fide independent contractor, to provide 'tasters' that will check on food quality. Subsequently, these 'tasters' joined the union of rank-and-file employees of Luningning and demanded that they be made regular employees of the latter as they are performing functions necessary and desirable to operate the company’s business. Luningning rejected the demand for regularization. On behalf of the 'tasters', the union then filed a notice of strike with the Department of Labor and Employment (DOLE). In response, Luningning sought a restraining order from the Regional Trial Court (RTC) arguing that the DOLE does not have jurisdiction over the case since it does not have an employer-employee relationship with the employees of an independent contractor. If you were the RTC judge, would you issue a restraining order against the union? (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. There is no labor dispute in the instant case. Since Lamitan Manpower is a bona fide independent contractor, there is no employee-employer relationship between the Luningning and the tasters. (Alternative: No. Article 254 of the Labor Code is clear that no temporary or permanent injunction or restraining order in any case involving or growing out of labor disputes shall be issued by any court or other entity, except as provided in Article 218 and 264 of the same Code.)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 92,
        "Question": "Constant Builders, an independent contractor, was charged with illegal dismissal and non-payment of wages and benefits of ten dismissed employees. The complainants impleaded as co-respondent Able Company, Constant Builder's principal in the construction of Able's office building. The complaint demanded that Constant and Able be held solidarily liable for the payment of their backwages, separation pay, and all their unpaid wages and benefits. If the Labor Arbiter rules in favor of the complainants, choose the statement that best describes the extent of the liabilities of Constant and Able. (2013 Bar Questions) (A) Constant and Able should be held solidarily liable for the unpaid wages and benefits, as well as backwages and separation pay, based on Article 109 of the Labor Code which provides that every employer or indirect employer shall be held responsible with his contractor or subcontractor for any violation of any provision of this Code. (B) Constant and Able should be held solidarily liable for the unpaid wages and benefits, and should order Constant, as the workers' direct employer, to be solely liable for the backwages and separation pay. (C) Constant and Able should be held solidarily liable for the unpaid wages and benefits and the backwages since these pertain to labor standard benefits for which the employer and contractor are liable under the law, while Constant alone – as the actual employer - should be ordered to pay the separation pay. (D) Constant and Able should be held solidarily liable for the unpaid wages and benefits, and Constant should be held liable for their backwages and separation pay unless Able is shown to have participated with malice or bad faith in the workers' dismissal, in which case both should be held solidarily liable. (E) The above statements are all inaccurate.",
        "Answer": "(A) Constant and Able should be held solidarily liable for the unpaid wages and benefits, as well as backwages and separation pay, based on Article 109 of the Labor Code which provides that every employer or indirect employer shall be held responsible with his contractor or subcontractor for any violation of any provision of this Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 93,
        "Question": "Star Crafts is a lantern maker based in Pampanga. It supplies Christmas lanterns to stores in Luzon, Metro Manila, and parts of Visayas, with the months of August to November being the busiest months. Its factory employs a workforce of 2,000 workers who make different lanterns daily for the whole year. Because of increased demand, Star Crafts entered into a contractual arrangement with People Plus, a service contractor, to supply the former with I 00 workers for only 4 months, August to November, at a rate different from what they pay their regular employees. The contract with People Plus stipulates that all equipment and raw materials will be supplied by Star Crafts with the express condition that the workers cannot take any of the designs home and must complete their tasks within the premises of Star Crafts. Is there an employer-employee relationship between Star Crafts and the 100 workers from People Plus? Explain. (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. People Plus is a labor-only-contractor because it is not substantially capitalized. Neither does it carry on an independent business in which it uses its own investment in the form of tools, equipment, machineries or work premises. Hence, it is just an agent or recruiter of workers who perform work directly related to the trade of Star Crafts. Since both the essential element and the conforming element of labor-only contracting are present, Star Crafts becomes the employer of the supplied worker."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 94,
        "Question": "XYZ Manpower Services (XYZ) was sued by its employees together with its client, ABC Polyester Manufacturing Company (ABC). ABC is one of the many clients of XYZ. During the proceedings before the Labor Arbiter, XYZ was able to prove that it had substantial capital of Three Million Pesos. The Labor Arbiter ruled in favor of the employees because it deemed XYZ as a labor only contractor. XYZ was not able to prove that it had invested in tools, equipment, etc. Is the Labor Arbiter's ruling valid? Explain.  (2012 BAR)",
        "Answer": "No, the Labor Arbiter’s ruling is not valid. Art. 106 of the Labor Code provides that the contractor has 'substantial capital or investment'. The law did not say substantial capital and investment, hence, it is in the alternative. Under Department Order No. 18-A, Series of 2011, the amount of P3 million paid-up capital for the company is substantial capital."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 95,
        "Question": "Does the performance by a contractual employee, supplied by a legitimate contractor, of activities directly related to the main business of the principal make him a regular employee of the principal? Explain.  (2012 BAR)",
        "Answer": "No. The element of an employee’s 'performing activities which are directly related to the principal business of such employer' does not actually matter for such is allowed by Art. 107 of the Labor Code. An 'independent contractor for the performance of any work, task, job or project' is allowed."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 96,
        "Question": "1) What is a 'labor-only contract? 2) Distinguish the liabilities of an employer who engages the services of a bona fide 'independent contractor from one who engages a 'labor-only contractor?",
        "Answer": "1) 'Labor-only contract is a contract between an employer and a person who supplies workers to such employer where the person supplying workers does not have substantial capital or investment in the form of tools, equipment, machineries, work premises, among others, and the workers recruited and placed by such person are performing activities which are directly related to the principal business of such employer (Art. 106, Labor Code). 2) A person who engages the services of a bona fide 'Independent contractor is the indirect employer of the employees who have been hired by the Independent contractor. In the event that the independent contractor fails to pay the wages of his employees, an indirect employer... is jointly and severally liable with the independent contractor to the employees of the latter to the extent of the work performed under the contract. As for the person who engages the services of a labor only contractor, the latter is considered merely as an agent of the former who shall be responsible to the workers hired by the 'labor only contractor in the same manner and extent as if he directly employed such workers."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 97,
        "Question": "Is the Service Agreement between Jolli-Mac and MMSI legal and valid? Why or why not?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. It is not legal and valid because MMSI is engaged in labor-only contracting. For one, the workers supplied by MMSI to Jolli-Mac are performing services which are directly related to the principal business of Jolli-Mac. For another, MMSI was organized by Jolli-Mac itself to supply its personnel requirements."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 98,
        "Question": "If the cashiers, delivery boys and food servers are not paid their lawful salaries, including overtime pay, holiday pay, 13,h month pay, and sendee incentive leave pay, against whom may these workers file their claims? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "They may file their claims against Jolli-Mac. A finding that MMSI is a 'labor-only' contractor is equivalent to declaring there is an employer-employee relationship between Jolli-Mac and the workers of MMSI. The liability of Jolli-Mac vis-a-vis the workers of MMSI is for a comprehensive purpose, i.e., not only for the unpaid wages but for all claims under the Labor Code and ancillary laws."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 99,
        "Question": "The Pizza Corporation (PizCorp) and Ready Supply Cooperative (RSC) entered into a 'service agreement'... PizCorp can directly impose disciplinary sanctions on, including the power to dismiss, the erring RSC member/s. Is RSC engaged in 'labor-only' contracting?",
        "Answer": "It is not enough to show substantial capitalization or investment in the form of tools, equipment, machinery and work premises. In addition, the following factors have to be considered: (a) whether the contractor is carrying on an independent business; (f) the control and supervision of the workers; (g) the power of employer with respect to the hiring, firing and payment of workers of the contractor."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 100,
        "Question": "Matatag Insurance does not have to await the result of the criminal case before exercising its prerogative to dismiss. (Implicit question: Is this action valid/correct?)",
        "Answer": "Matatag Insurance does not have to await the result of the criminal case before exercising its prerogative to dismiss. Dismissal is not affected by a criminal case. The evidence of the ground for dismissal is substantial evidence only. Hence, Rico’s conviction need not precede the employee’s dismissal."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 101,
        "Question": "Under current jurisprudence, when the dismissal is for a just or authorized cause but due process is not observed, the dismissal is said to be: (2012 Bar Question) a. Void for denial of due process; hence, the employee should be reinstated; b. Void for lack of due process, the employee should be paid full backwages; c. Valid, for the dismissal is with just/authorized cause, but the employer shall be liable for nominal damages; d. Valid, even if due process is not observed, hence reinstatement should not be ordered.",
        "Answer": "c. Valid, for the dismissal is with just/authorized cause, but the employer shall be liable for nominal damages;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 102,
        "Question": "Lionel, an American citizen whose parents migrated to the U.S. from the Philippines, was hired by JP Morgan in New York as a call center specialist. Hearing about the phenomenal growth of the call center industry in his parents’ native land, Lionel sought and was granted a transfer as a call center manager for JP Morgan’s operations in Taguig City. Lionel’s employment contract did not specify a period for his stay in the Philippines. After three years of working in the Philippines, Lionel was advised that he was being recalled to New York and being promoted to the position of director of international call center operations. However, because of certain 'family reasons,' Lionel advised the company of his preference to stay in the Philippines. He was dismissed by the company. Lionel now seeks your legal advice on: (A) whether he has a cause of action (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will dismiss the case. ADB enjoys immunity from suit (DFA vs. NLRC, G.R. No. 113191, September 18, 1996)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 103,
        "Question": "What are the grounds for validly terminating the services of an employee based on a just cause?  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Article 296 of the Labor Code (formerly Article 282) provides for the termination of the services of an employee for just causes. An employer may terminate an employment for any of the following causes: (a) **Serious misconduct** or willful disobedience by the employee of the lawful orders of his employer- or representative in connection with his work; (b) **Gross and habitual neglect** by the employee of his duties; (c) **Fraud or willful breach of trust** by the employee of the employer’s or his representative’s trust and confidence; (d) **Loss of confidence**; (e) **Commission of a crime or offense** by the employee against the person of his employer or any immediate member of his family or his duly authorized representatives; and (f) **Other analogous causes**."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 104,
        "Question": "Is his claim for salaries for the unexpired portion of his contract tenable? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "YES. Section 10 of Rep. Act No. 8042 (as amended by Rep. Act No. 10022) provides that in case of termination of overseas employment without just, valid or authorized cause... the worker shall be entitled to the full reimbursement of his placement fee with interest at twelve percent (12%) per annum, plus his salaries for the unexpired portion of his employment contract or for three (3) years for every year of the unexpired term, whichever is less."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 105,
        "Question": "Did Renan commit acts of sexual harassment in a work-related or employment environment? Reasons. ",
        "Answer": "YES. Atty. Renan committed sexual harassment because his superior position over Maganda gave him authority, influence or moral ascendancy over her, and his repeated requests for a date, coupled with a statement of a condition for her career advancement, created a hostile, intimidating or offensive work environment. His acts showed grave and aggravated character and committed in connection with his work."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 106,
        "Question": "Diosdado, a carpenter, was hired by Building Industries Corporation (BIC), and assigned to build a small house in Alabang. His contract of employment specifically referred to him as a 'project employee,' although it did not provide any particular date of completion of the project. Is the completion of the house a valid cause for the termination of Diosdado’s employment? If so, what are the due process requirements that the BIC must satisfy? If not, why not?  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The completion of the house should be valid cause for termination of Diosdado’s employment. Although the employment contract may not state a particular date, but if it did specify that the termination of the parties' employment relationship was to be on a 'day certain' - the day when the phase of work would be completed - the employee cannot be considered to have been a regular employee. To satisfy due process requirement, under DOLE Department Order No. 19, series of 1993, the employer is required to report to the relevant DOLE Regional Office the fact of termination of project employees as a result of the completion of the project or any phase thereof in which one is employed."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 107,
        "Question": "For misconduct or improper behavior to be a just cause for dismissal, the following guidelines must be met, except: (2012 Bar Question) a) It must be serious; b) It must relate to the performance of the employee’s duties; c) It should not be used as a subterfuge for causes which are improper, illegal or unjustified; d) It must show that the employee has become unfit to continue working for the employer.",
        "Answer": "c) It should not be used as a subterfuge for causes which are improper, illegal or unjustified."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 108,
        "Question": "The Supreme Court categorically declared that separation pay shall be allowed as a measure of social justice only in those instances where the employee is validly dismissed for cause other than: (2012 Bar Question) a. Serious Misconduct; b. Gross and habitual neglect of duties; c. Willfull disobedience to lawful orders; d. Fraud or willful breach of trust.",
        "Answer": "a. Serious Misconduct."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 109,
        "Question": "Luisa was hired as a secretary by the Asian Development Bank (ADB) in Manila. Luisa’s first boss was a Japanese national whom she got along with. But after two years, the latter was replaced by an arrogant Indian national who did not believe her work output was in accordance with international standards. One day, Luisa submitted a draft report filled with typographical errors to her boss. The latter scolded her, but Luisa verbally fought back. The Indian boss decided to terminate her services right then and there. Luisa filed a case for illegal dismissal with the Labor Arbiter claiming arbitrariness and denial of due process. If you were the Labor Arbiter, how would you decide the case? (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will dismiss the case. ADB enjoys immunity from suit (DFA vs. NLRC, G.R. No. 113191, September 18, 1996)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 110,
        "Question": "Lanz was a strict and unpopular Vice-President for Sales of Lobinsons Land. One day, Lanz shouted invectives against Lee, a poor performing sales associate, calling him, among others, a 'brown monkey.' Hurt, Lee decided to file a criminal complaint for grave defamation against Lanz. The prosecutor found probable cause and filed an information in court. Lobinsons decided to terminate Lanz for committing a potential crime and other illegal acts prejudicial to business. Can Lanz be legally terminated by the company on these grounds? (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. The grounds relied upon by Lobinsons are not just causes for dismissal under the Labor Code. Defamation is not a crime against person which is a ground to dismiss under Article 282, now Article 295, (d) of the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 111,
        "Question": "What is the successor employer doctrine?  (2015 BAR)",
        "Answer": "The 'successor employer' doctrine refers to a sales or transfer in ownership of an entity that has been done in bad faith or to defeat the rights of labor. In such a case, it is as if there have been no changes in employer-employee relationship between the seller and its employees. The buyer becomes a 'successor employer' and is obliged to absorb the displaced employees."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 112,
        "Question": "ABC Tomato Corporation, owned and managed by three (3) elderly brothers and two (2) sisters, has been in business for 40 years. Due to serious business losses and financial reverses during the last five (5) years, they decided to close the business. As counsel for the corporation, what steps will you take prior to its closure?  (2012 BAR)",
        "Answer": "I will serve a written notice on both the workers and the Regional Office of the Department of Labor and Employment, at least one (1) month before the intended date of closure (Art. 283, Labor Code); and provide proof of ABC’s serious business losses or financial reverses."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 113,
        "Question": "Are the employees entitled to separation pay?  (2012 BAR) (Context: Closure due to serious business losses.)",
        "Answer": "No. Where closure is due to serious business losses, no separation pay is required."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 114,
        "Question": "If the reason for the closure is due to old age of the brothers and sisters: c. Is the closure allowed by law?  (2012 BAR)",
        "Answer": "Yes. The determination to cease or suspend operations is a prerogative of management that the State usually does not interfere with, as no business can be required to continue operating to simply maintain the workers in employment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 115,
        "Question": "Are the employees entitled to separation benefits?  (2012 BAR) (Context: Closure not due to serious business losses.)",
        "Answer": "Yes. In case of cessation of operations of establishment or undertaking not due to serious business losses or financial reverses, the separation pay shall be equivalent to one (1) month pay or at least one-half (1/2) month pay for every year of service, whichever is higher. A fraction of at least six (6) months shall be considered as one (1) whole year."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 116,
        "Question": "Aside from the just causes enumerated in Article 282 of the Labor Code for the termination of employment, state three (3) lawful or authorized causes for the dismissal of an employee. ",
        "Answer": "According to Art. 283 of the Labor Code, the lawful or authorized causes for the termination of an employee are: 1. installation of labor saving devices 2. redundancy 3. retrenchment to prevent losses or; 4. closing or cessation of operation of the establishment or undertaking, unless the closing Is for the purpose of circumventing the provisions of the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 117,
        "Question": "Coronet Records Phil. (CRP)... decided to sell all its assets to Lyra Music Corporation effective September 30. 1993... The Arbiter ruled in favor of the workers and ordered Lyra Music Corporation to absorb the former workers of CRP. Was the Labor Arbiter correct in his decision?",
        "Answer": "No. The Labor Arbiter is not correct. When there is a legitimate sale of a company’s assets, the buyer in good faith cannot be legally compelled to absorb the employees of the seller in good faith. In the case at bar, the employees of the CRP were validly terminated based on Article 284, e.g. closure of operations and separation pay was paid at a rate much higher than the law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 118,
        "Question": "Is Nelle correct in claiming that she was illegally dismissed?  (Context: Zienna sold all assets to Zandra, Nelle was terminated but accepted separation pay.)",
        "Answer": "No. In asset sales, the corporate entity sells all or substantially all of its assets to another entity. Zienna is authorized to dismiss its employees, but must pay separation pay. The buyer Zandra, is not obliged to absorb the employees affected by the sale, nor is it liable for the payment of their claims."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 119,
        "Question": "Bugoy, an employee with only six (6) months of service, was dismissed due to redundancy. He is, under Art. 283 of the Labor Code, entitled to a separation pay of: (2012 Bar Question) a. One (1) month pay; b. One (1) year pay. Art. 283 of the Labor Code being explicit that 'a fraction of at least six (6) months shall be considered one (1) whole year; c. Six (6) months pay; d. One (1) year and six (6) months pay, as Art. 4 of the Labor Code mandated that '(a)ll doubts in the implementation and interpretation of this Code xxx shall be resolved in favor of labor'.",
        "Answer": "a) One (1) month pay."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 120,
        "Question": "Luisa Court is a popular chain of motels. It employs over 30 chambermaids... Luisa Court decided to abolish the position of chambermaids and outsource the cleaning of the rooms to Malinis Janitorial Services, a bona fide independent contractor... The chambermaids filed a case of illegal dismissal against Luisa Court. In response, the company argued that the decision to outsource resulted from the new management’s directive to streamline operations and save on costs. If you were the Labor Arbiter assigned to the case, how would you decide? (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will decide in favor of Luisa Court, provided that all the requisites for a valid retrenchment under the Labor Code are satisfied. It is management prerogative to farm out any of its activities."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 121,
        "Question": "Venus Department Store decided to contract out the security services that its 10 direct-hired full-time security guards provided. The company paid the men separation pay. With this move, the Store was able to cut costs and secure efficient outside professional security services. But the terminated security guards complained of illegal dismissal, claiming that regular jobs such as theirs could not be contracted out. Will their complaint prosper? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "No. The jobs were given to job contractors, not to labor-only contractors, and the dismissed employees received higher separation pay than the law required."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 122,
        "Question": "What legal requisite must the employer observe to validly cease its operations? (2011 BAR) (A) Instead of giving a 30-day notice, she can just give a 30-day advanced salary and make the separation effective immediately. (B) So long as she gave DOLE a 30-day prior notice, she can give the employees a shorter notice. (C) The 30-day advance notice to the employee and the DOLE cannot be shortened even with a 30-day advance salary. (D) She can give a shorter notice if the retrenchment is due to severe and substantial losses.",
        "Answer": "(C) The 30-day advance notice to the employee and the DOLE cannot be shortened even with a 30-day advance salary."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 123,
        "Question": "A sugar mill in Laguna, capitalized at P300 million, suffered a P10,000.00 loss last year. This year it dismissed three young female employees who gave birth in the last three years. In its termination report to DOLE, the sugar mill gave as reason for the dismissal 'retrenchment because of losses.' Did it violate any law? (2011 BAR) (A) Yes, the law on retrenchment, the sugar mill’s loses not being substantial. (B) Yes, the law against violence committed on women and children. (C) No, except the natural law that calls for the protection and support of women. (D) No, but the management action confirms suspicion that some companies avoid hiring women because of higher costs.",
        "Answer": "(A) Yes, the law on retrenchment, the sugar mill’s loses not being substantial."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 124,
        "Question": "Give the procedure to be observed for validly terminating the services of an employee based on a just cause? (4%) (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Procedural due process mandates that the twin requirements of Notice and Hearing should be present. The two notices are as follows: 1st notice: **Notice of appraisal**, which is a written notice served on the employee specifying the ground or grounds of termination, and giving the employee reasonable opportunity within which to explain his side. 2nd notice: **Notice of termination**, which is a written notice of termination served upon the employee, indicating that upon due consideration of all the circumstances, grounds have been established to justify his termination."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 125,
        "Question": "Explain the twin notice and hearing rule. (2016)",
        "Answer": "The twin notice and hearing rule requires a directive that the employee be given the opportunity to submit a written explanation on why he should not be dismissed within a reasonable period of time. The grounds for terminating an employee... must be a detailed narration of the facts and circumstances that will support the charge against the employee. Then the employer must inform the employee in writing of its decision stating the facts, the analysis of the evidence and statement of witnesses and the law or policy which led to the decision."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 126,
        "Question": "Did the Biyahe sa Langit Transport comply with the prior procedural requirements for dismissal?",
        "Answer": "No. The notice given by Biyahe sa Langit Transport did not give Pedro a minimum period."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 127,
        "Question": "If an employer's dismissal of an employee is declared illegal for failure to observe due process, what is the consequence? (2011 BAR) (A) defective; the dismissal process has to be repeated. (B) an abuse of employer's discretion, rendering the dismissal void. (C) ineffectual; the dismissal will be held in abeyance. (D) legal and valid but the employer will be liable for indemnity.",
        "Answer": "(D) legal and valid but the employer will be liable for indemnity."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 128,
        "Question": "Juan Santos is a regular employee of Far East Development Company... dismissed... The employer argued that even if there was no due process in the dismissal... it was found that the dismissal was for a just cause and therefore Santos was not entitled to reinstatement. (1) Is the employer's contention valid? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The employer's contention is valid. The dismissal is declared legal if based on a just or authorized cause. In such a case, the employer's failure to give notice and hearing does not amount to illegal dismissal, but merely to a violation of procedural due process, for which the employee is entitled to nominal damages."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 129,
        "Question": "Santos, on the other hand, challenged the proceedings before the labor arbiter on the ground that no hearing was conducted and that the decision was reached only on the basis of position papers submitted and hence, in violation of due process. (2) Is the contention of Santos correct? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The contention of Santos is not correct. The Labor Arbiter is not prevented from deciding a case on the basis of the position papers alone. The Labor Arbiter may, but is not required to, conduct a formal hearing for the reception or presentation of evidence."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 130,
        "Question": "What are the twin-requirements of due process which the employer must observe in terminating or dismissing an employee? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "The twin requirements of due process are **notice and hearing** to be given to the worker. There is likewise a two-notice requirement rule, with the first notice pertaining to specific causes or grounds for termination and a directive to submit a written explanation within a reasonable period. The second notice pertains to notice of termination."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 131,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a procedural due process requirement in the termination of an employee for just cause? (2012 Bar Question) a. A written notice to the employee specifying the grounds for his termination; b. A written notice to the DOLE at least thirty (30) days before the effectivity of the termination; c. An opportunity to be heard; d. A written notice of termination.",
        "Answer": "b. A written notice to the DOLE at least thirty (30) days before the effectivity of the termination."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 132,
        "Question": "May Mandarin Company recover the backwages and other benefits paid to Juanito pursuant to the decision of the Labor Arbiter in view of the reversal by the NLRC? Rule, with reasons.  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Mandarin cannot recover the backwages and other benefits paid to Juanito. The decision of the Labor Arbiter insofar as the reinstatement aspect is concerned, is immediately executory pending appeal. It is the obligation of Mandarin to immediately admit Juanito back to work or reinstate him in the payroll."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 133,
        "Question": "When is separation pay granted in lieu of reinstatement? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "Separation pay is granted in lieu of reinstatement when: (a) reinstatement is no longer feasible due to the closure or cessation of operation of the establishment or undertaking of the employer not founded on serious business losses; or (b) the former position of the employee no longer exists at the time of reinstatement for reasons not attributable to the fault of the employer; or (c) the existence of strained relations between the employer and the illegally dismissed employee, provided the matter is raised before the Labor Arbiter."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 134,
        "Question": "What is meant by payroll reinstatement and when does it apply? (4%) (2005 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Payroll reinstatement is a form of reinstatement which an employer may opt to exercise in lieu of an actual reinstatement. Here, the illegally dismissed employee is to receive his basic pay without the obligation of rendering any service to the employer. This occurs when a Labor Arbiter decides that an employee was illegally dismissed and as a consequence awards reinstatement, pursuant to Article 279 of the Labor Code, which award is immediately executory even pending appeal."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 135,
        "Question": "Suppose Juan Dukha proved during the hearing that he was robbed of his collections and, consequently, the Labor Arbiter decided in his favor. In the meantime, the Ladies Garments Company appealed to the National Labor Relations Commission (NLRC). Pending appeal, what rights are available to Juan relative to the favorable decision of the Labor Arbiter? Explain. (1995 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Juan can ask for immediate reinstatement pending resolution of the appeal filed by the company with the NLRC. At the option of his employer, he may be admitted back to work or merely reinstated in the payroll."
    },
    // FIX: Remove 'page_range' property
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 136,
        "Question": "If the Labor Arbiter finds that the dismissal was illegal for being without just cause, what relief/s may be granted to Juan?",
        "Answer": "Juan is entitled to these reliefs, namely reinstatement without loss of seniority and other privileges and full backwages, inclusive of allowances, and to other benefits or their monetary equivalent computed from the time his compensation was withheld from him up to the time of his actual reinstatement."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 137,
        "Question": "Reinstatement is not barred by: (2012 Bar Question) (A) there is a strained employer-employee relationship (B) the position of the employee no longer exists (C) the employer’s business has been closed (D) the employee does not wish to be reinstated.",
        "Answer": "(D) the employee does not wish to be reinstated."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 138,
        "Question": "The decision of the Labor Arbiter in a labor dispute case is: (2012 Bar Question) a. Immediately executory; b. Requires a writ of execution; c. Is immediately executor insofar as the reinstatement of the employee is concerned; d. Is stayed by the appeal of the employer and posting of appeal bond.",
        "Answer": "c. Is immediately executory insofar as the reinstatement of the employee is concerned."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 139,
        "Question": "An employee proved to have been illegally dismissed is entitled to reinstatement and full backwages computed on the basis of his (2011 BAR) (A) basic salary plus the regular allowances and the thirteenth month pay. (B) basic salary plus the salary CBA increases during the pendency of his case. (C) basic salary plus the increases mandated by wage orders issued during the pendency of his case. (D) basic salary plus all allowances and other benefits, or their monetary equivalent, corresponding to the period of his illegal dismissal.",
        "Answer": "(D) basic salary plus all allowances and other benefits, or their monetary equivalent, corresponding to the period of his illegal dismissal."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 140,
        "Question": "May the general manager of a company be held jointly and severally liable for backwages of an illegally dismissed employee? ",
        "Answer": "Yes. If it is shown that he acted in bad faith, or without or In excess of authority, or was motivated by personal ill-will in dismissing the employee, the general manager may be held jointly and severally liable for the backwages of an illegally dismissed employee."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 141,
        "Question": "Is the preventive suspension of Karina valid? Discuss the reasons for your answer. (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. The preventive suspension of Karina is not valid. The employer may place an employee under preventive suspension if his/her continued employment would pose a serious and imminent threat to the life or property of the employer or of his/her co-employees. These requirements are not present here."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 142,
        "Question": "An accidental fire gutted the JKL factory in Caloocan. JKL decided to suspend operations and requested its employees to stop reporting for work. After six (6) months, JKL resumed operations but hired a new set of employees. The old set of employees filed a case for illegal dismissal. If you were the Labor Arbiter, how would you decide the case? (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will rule in favor of the employees. JKL factory merely suspended its operations as a result of the fire that gutted its factory. Article 286 of the Labor Code states that an employer may bona fide suspend the operation of its business for a period not exceeding six (6) months. Since, the suspension of work lasted more than six months, there is now constructive dismissal."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 143,
        "Question": "Harbor View Hotel has an existing Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) with the union of rank-and-file employees... During the lifetime of the CBA, Harbor View Hotel, for reasons of economy and efficiency, decided to abolish the position of housemen and stewards... and contracted out the aforementioned job to the City Service Janitorial Company, a bonafide independent contractor... Is the action of the Harbor View Hotel legal and valid?",
        "Answer": "The action of Harbor View Hotel is legal and valid."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 144,
        "Question": "Bulacan Medical Hospital (BMH) entered into a Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) with its Union... expressly stipulated in the Management Prerogative Clause that BMH shall... have the sole and exclusive right to promulgate, amend and modify rules and regulations... The Union wrote BMH demanding that the Revised Rules and Regulations be first discussed with them before its implementation. BMH refused. So. the Union filed an action for unfair labor practice (ULP) against BMH. 1) Is the Union correct?",
        "Answer": "The Union is correct. A provision in the collective bargaining agreement concerning management prerogatives, may not be interpreted as cession of the employees’ right to participate in the deliberation of matters which may affect their right and the formulation of policies relative thereto, such as the formulation of a code of discipline. Workers have the right to participate in policy and decision-making processes affecting their rights, benefits and welfare (Art. 255)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 145,
        "Question": "Assuming that the CBA was signed or executed before the 1987 Constitution was ratified, would your answer to the preceding question be different?",
        "Answer": "The answer would be the same even if the CBA was signed or executed before the ratification of the 1987 Constitution because it has always been the policy of the State to promote the enlightenment of workers concerning their rights and obligations as employees (Art. 211; PAL vs. NLRC, GR 85985. August 13. 1993)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 146,
        "Question": "Bobby, who was assigned as company branch accountant in Tarlac... was dismissed... ordered reinstated with full backwages... Theta Company appealed... and at the same time wrote Bobby, advising him to report to the main company office in Makati where he would be reinstated pending appeal... Bobby refused... (A) Is Bobby's reinstatement pending appeal legally correct? (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "No. it is not really correct. The reinstatement of Bobby ought to be to his former position, much akin to return to work order, i.e. to restore the status quo in the work place."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 147,
        "Question": "What Clinton's cause of action, if any, against Perot Drug Company?",
        "Answer": "The course of action of Clinton against Perot Drug Company is that of illegal dismissal. When the Company dismissed him for his refusal to be promoted and transferred 'for family reason, he could claim he was being dismissed without just cause."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 148,
        "Question": "If he has a cause of action, where will you file the appropriate petition — in the U.S. or in the Philippines?",
        "Answer": "I will file the case of illegal dismissal in the Philippines where Clinton was working when he was dismissed. The Company can be sued in the Philippines because it is doing business in the country by having a branch in Manila."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 149,
        "Question": "Will your petition, if you decide to file one, proper? Answer with reasons.",
        "Answer": "The petition will prosper. The refusal of Clinton to be promoted and transferred to Cleveland is not just cause. His refusing a promotion... cannot be considered as willful disobedience of a lawful order of his employer. Thus, there is not just cause for the dismissal of Clinton."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 150,
        "Question": "Din Din is a single mother... transferred to the Visayas. Din Din does not want to uproot her family and refuses the offer. Her boss is so humiliated by Din Din's refusal... she gives Din Din successive unsatisfactory evaluations that result in Din Din being removed... What would you advise her? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will advise Din Din to sue her boss and the supermarket for illegal dismissal. Din Din cannot be compelled to accept the promotion. Her unsatisfactory evaluations as well as her boss’ insistence that she should agree to the intended transfer to Visayas are badges of an abuse of management prerogative. Hence, Din Din’s dismissal is illegal."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 151,
        "Question": "Union 'X' is the majority union of the rank and file employees at Slipper Mart Company. It amended its by-laws to include among the obligations of its members 'to refuse to work with non-union members.' Slipper Mart wants the amendment to be declared null and void considering that not all its rank and file employees belong to Union 'X' and its enforcement will cause work stoppage in the company. Give your opinion on the validity of the amendment.",
        "Answer": "The provision of the by-laws of the union that made it among the obligations of its members ‘‘to refuse to work with non-union members' cannot be implemented at the Slipper Mart Company. It is management’s prerogative to determine who shall work together in a company. (Alternative: The act is an unfair labor practice on the part of the union because it could have the effect of compelling the employer to compel its employees to join Union 'X'...)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 152,
        "Question": "What is a bonus? When is it demandable as a matter of right? Explain.",
        "Answer": "A bonus is money given in addition to an employee’s usual compensation. It may be given as a gratuity, as an act of liberality. But a bonus is demandable as a matter of right if it is made a legal obligation by law or in a collective bargaining agreement or in a contract of employment or by its having been given for such a long time such that the receipt of a bonus has ripened into a right."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 153,
        "Question": "Inter-Garments Co. manufactures garments for export... Since 2009, it has been paying its employees on overtime an additional 35% of their hourly rate... in 2012, it adjusted the overtime rates so that those who worked overtime were only paid an additional 25% instead of the previous 35%. To replace the workers' overtime rate loss, the company granted a one-time 5% across-the-board wage increase. Vigilant Union... charged the company with Unfair Labor Practice on the ground that (1) no consultations had been made on who would render overtime work; and (2) the unilateral overtime pay rate reduction is a violation of Article 100 (entitled Prohibition Against Elimination or Diminution of Benefits) of the Labor Code. Is the union position meritorious? (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "The allegation of ULP by the Union is not meritorious regarding consultation. The selection as to who would render overtime work is a management prerogative. However, the charge of the Union on the diminution of benefits... appears to be meritorious. Since three (3) years have already lapsed, the overtime rate of 35% has ripened into practice and policy, and cannot anymore be removed."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 154,
        "Question": "Seventy (70) private security guards of TAPANG SECURITY AGENCY CORPORATION, assigned to guard the mining area of DAVAO GOLD CORPORATION... filed a complaint... for failure... to remit its contributions to the System. Who is deemed an 'employee for purposes of coverage under the SSS law?",
        "Answer": "A person is deemed an employee for purposes of coverage under the Social Security Law if such person performs services for an employer in which either or both mental and physical efforts are used and who received compensation for such services, where there is an employer-employee relationship. Also, a self-employed person is both an employee and employer at the same time."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 155,
        "Question": "Can a member of a cooperative be deemed an employee for purposes of compulsory' coverage under the Social Security Act? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes, an employee of a cooperative, not over sixty (60) years of age is, under the SSS Law, subject to compulsory coverage. The Section 8(d) SSS Law defines an employee as — 'Sec. 8(d)— any person who performs services for an employer in which either or both mental and physical efforts are used and who receives compensation for such service, where there is an employer- employee relationship."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 156,
        "Question": "Don Jose, a widower, owns a big house with a large garden... He chanced upon Mang Kiko on the street and asked him to water the plants and clean the house. He finished the work in two days. Are they compulsorily covered by the Social Security System?",
        "Answer": "No. In their employer-employee relationship, Don Jose and Mang Kiko are not compulsory covered by the Social Security System because Mang Kiko is rendering domestic services in a private home which is one of the kinds of employment excluded from the compulsory coverage of the Social Security System."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 157,
        "Question": "Tito Paciencioso is an employee of a foundry shop in Malabon, Metro Manila... he asked his employer to stop deducting from his salary his SSS monthly contribution, reasoning out that he is waiving his social security coverage. If you were Tito’s employer, would you grant his request? Why?",
        "Answer": "No. As Tito’s employer, I am bound by law to remit to SSS Tito’s monthly contribution. The compulsory coverage of employers and employees under the SSS law is actually a legal imposition on the employers and employees, designed to provide social security to workingmen. Membership in SSS is in compliance with a lawful exercise of the police power of the State, and may not be waived by agreement of any party."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not considered an employer by the terms of the Social Security Act? (2012 Bar Question) a. A self employed person; b. The government and any of its political subdivisions, branches or instrumentalities, including corporations owned or controlled by the government; c. A natural persons, domestic or foreign, who carries on in undertaking or activity of any kind and uses the services of another person who is under his orders as regards the employment; d. A foreign corporation.",
        "Answer": "b) The government and any of its political subdivisions, branches or instrumentalities, including corporations owned or controlled by the government."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 159,
        "Question": "Falcon Factory is engaged in the assembling of automotive components... hired fifty (50) persons (engineers, architects and construction workers) to renovate its building... The workers contend that they are casual employees who are not subject to compulsory coverage under the Social Security Law. Do you agree with their contention? Explain your answer fully. ",
        "Answer": "Yes. Under Section 8 (j) of RA 1161, as amended, employment of purely casual and not for the purpose of the occupation or business of the employer are excepted from compulsory coverage. The work to be performed by these fifty (50) people is not in connection with the purpose of the business of the factory. Hence, the employ of these fifty (50) persons is purely casual. They are, therefore, excepted from the compulsory coverage of the SSS law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 160,
        "Question": "Who may be the legal dependents of Gene under the Social Security Law?  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Pursuant to Section 8(e) of Rep. Act No. 1161, the legal dependents Of Gene under the Social Security Law are the legitimate, legitimated or legally adopted child who is unmarried, not gainfully employed and not over twenty-one years of age, or over twenty-one years of age provided that he is congenitally incapacitated and incapable of self-support, physically or mentally; the legitimate spouse dependent for support upon the employee; and the legitimate parents wholly dependent upon the covered employee for regular support."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 161,
        "Question": "Jennifer, a receptionist at Company X, is covered by the SSS. She was pregnant with her fourth child when she slipped in the bathroom of her home and had a miscarriage. Meanwhile, Company X neglected to remit the required contributions to the SSS. Jennifer claims maternity leave benefits and sickness benefits. Which of these two may she claim? (2012 Bar Question) a. None of them; b. Either one of them; c. Only maternity leave benefits; d. Only sickness benefits.",
        "Answer": "c. Only maternity leave benefits;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 162,
        "Question": "Luisa is an unwed mother with 3 children from different fathers. In 2004, she became a member of the Social Security System (SSS). That same year, she suffered a miscarriage of a baby out of wedlock from the father of her third child. She wants to claim maternity benefits under the SSS Act. Is she entitled to claim? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. Provided Luisa has reported to her employer her pregnancy and date of expected delivery and paid at least three monthly contributions during the 12-month period immediately preceding her miscarriage then she is entitled to maternity benefits up to four deliveries. As to the fact that she got pregnant outside wedlock... this will not bar her claim because the SSS is non-discriminatory."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 163,
        "Question": "A is an employee of B who in turn registered A with the Social Security System as required by law. Unfortunately, B did not remit A’s contributions to the System. In the course of his employment, A met a serious accident requiring his hospitalization. (1) Suppose he decides to retire from the firm because of the accident, is he entitled to recover retirement benefits under the System? Explain your answer.",
        "Answer": "A is entitled to receive benefits from the Social Security System even if his employer did not remit A’s contribution to the System because the Social Security Law provides... that the failure or refusal of the employer to pay or remit contributions shall not prejudice the right of the covered employee to the benefits of the coverage. But A is not entitled to retirement benefits in the form of a monthly pension unless at the time of the accident, he has reached the age of sixty years and has paid at least 120 monthly contributions prior to the semester of the accident."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 164,
        "Question": "Suppose that he died because of the accident, are his heirs entitled to death benefits under the System? Explain your answer.",
        "Answer": "The heirs are not entitled, but his primary beneficiaries or in the absence of primary beneficiaries, his secondary beneficiaries are entitled."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 165,
        "Question": "State briefly the compulsory coverage of the Government Service Insurance Act.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The following are compulsorily covered by the GSIS pursuant to Sec. 3 of R.A. No. 8291: 1. All employees receiving compensation who have not reached the compulsory retirement age, irrespective of employment status. 2. Members of the judiciary and constitutional commissions for life insurance policy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 166,
        "Question": "Efrenia Reyes was a classroom teacher... GSIS denied the claim stating that after Efrenia's retirement, any progression of her ailment is no longer compensable. Is the GSIS correct in denying the claim. Explain.",
        "Answer": "No. When an employee is constrained to retire at an early age due to his illness and the illness persists even after retirement, resulting in his continued unemployment, such condition amounts to total disability which should entitle him to the maximum benefits allowed by law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 167,
        "Question": "Luisito has been working with Lima Land for 20 years. Wanting to work in the public sector, Luisito applied with and was offered a job at Livecor. Before accepting the offer, he wanted to consult you whether the payments that he and Lima Land had made to the Social Security System (SSS) can be transferred or credited to the Government Service Insurance System (GSIS). What would you advice? (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "I will advise Luisito that under the Limited Portability Law, R.A. 7699, he can transfer or credit his SSS contributions to the GSIS."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 168,
        "Question": "When a covered employee under the SSS law is transferred to the government service, the contributions made to the SSS shall be (2011 BAR) (A) credited only once. (B) credited in full. (C) proportionately reduced. (D) equally divided for the purpose of totalization.",
        "Answer": "(B) credited in full."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 169,
        "Question": "Rosa was granted vacation leave by her employer to spend three weeks in Africa with her family... The General Manager... requested her to visit the plant of a client of the company in Zimbabwe... It appears that she contracted a serious disease during the trip... Is the serious disease Rosa contracted during her trip to Africa compensable? Explain your answer.  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. For sickness and the resulting disability to be compensable... it is required that the sickness and the resulting injury must have arisen out of or in the course of employment. In the present case/ Rosa contracted the disease while on vacation leave. Consequently, the disease contracted by her in Africa during her vacation leave is not compensable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 170,
        "Question": "An employee’s sickness is compensable under the Employees Compensation Law if: (2012 Bar Question) a. There is a need to categorize a disability as permanent and total; b. It is not clear as to how an injury was sustained; c. The ailment or sickness is not classified as an occupational disease; d. There is a prima facie finding that the employee had willful intention to hurt himself.",
        "Answer": "c) The ailment or sickness is not classified as an occupational disease."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 171,
        "Question": "Which of the following injuries/death is not compensable? (2012 Bar Question) a. Injuries sustained by a technician while at a field trip initiated by the Union and sponsored by the Company; b. Injuries received by a janitor at a Union election meeting; c. Death of a bank teller because of a bank robbery; d. Death of a professor who was hit by a van on his way home from work.",
        "Answer": "b. Injuries received by a janitor at a Union election meeting;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 172,
        "Question": "Luis, a PNP officer, was off duty and resting at home when he heard a scuffle outside his house... rushed out to pacify them... shot Luis by mistake... The GSIS denied the claim... on the ground that the death of Luis was not service related as he was off duty... Is the GSIS correct? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. The GSIS is not correct. Luis, a policeman, just like a soldier, is covered by the 24-Hour Duty Rule. He is deemed on round-the-clock duty unless on official leave, in which case his death outside performance of official peace-keeping mission will bar death claim. In this case, Luis was not on official leave and he died in the performance of a peace-keeping mission. Therefore, his death is compensable."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 173,
        "Question": "Victor was hired by a local manning agency as a seafarer cook... While on board, Victor complained of chronic coughing... examination revealed that he had tuberculosis. (a) Victor sued for medical reimbursement, damages and attorney's fees, claiming that tuberculosis was a compensable illness. Do you agree with Victor? Why or why not? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "TB is listed under Sec. 32-A of the POEA-SEC as a work-related disease. It was also either contracted or aggravated during the effectivity of Victor’s contract. Having shown its manifestations on board, Victor should have been medically repatriated for further examination and treatment in the Philippines. This obligation was entirely omitted in bad faith by the company when it waited for his contract to expire on him before signing him off. On this basis, Victor is entitled to medical reimbursement, damages and attorney's fees."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 174,
        "Question": "Due to his prolonged illness, Victor was unable to work for more than 120 days. Will this entitle him to claim total permanent disability benefits? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. Under the law, a claim for total permanent disability shall be granted where the medical condition requires prolonged treatment, which lasts for more than 120 days. The rule is that the continued inability to work for 120 days warrants total permanent disability benefits."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 175,
        "Question": "Malou is the Executive Secretary of the Senior Vice- President of a bank while Ana is the Legal Secretary of the bank's lawyer. They and other executive secretaries would like to join the union of rank and file employees of the bank. Are they eligible to join the union? Why? Explain briefly. ",
        "Answer": "No right of self-organization for Legal Secretaries — Legal Secretaries fall under the category of confidential employees with no right to self-organization. Confidential employees are those who assist or act in a confidential capacity to persons who formulate, determine, and effectuate management policies in the field of labor-management relations."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 176,
        "Question": "It is defined as any union or association of employees which exists in whole or in part for the purpose of collective bargaining with employers concerning terms and conditions of employment. (2012 Bar Question) a. Bargaining representative; b. Labor organization; c. Legitimate labor organization; d. Federation.",
        "Answer": "b. Labor organization;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 177,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a right and/or condition of membership in a labor organization? (2012 Bar Question) a. No arbitrary or excessive initiation fees shall be required of the members of a legitimate labor organization; b. The members shall be entitled to full and detailed reports from their officers and representatives of all financial transactions; c. The members shall have the right to elect officers by secret ballot at intervals of not more than five (5) years; d. All of the above.",
        "Answer": "d. All of the above."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 178,
        "Question": "The legal personality of a labor organization is acquired from the date: (2012 Bar Question) a. The application for registration is filed; b. The constitution and by-laws are submitted to the DOLE; c. On the date appearing on the Certificate of Registration; d. On the date the Certificate of Registration is actually issued.",
        "Answer": "d. On the date the Certificate of Registration is actually issued."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following groups does not enjoy the right to self-organization? (2014 Bar Question) (A) those who work in a non-profit charitable institution (B) those who are paid on a piece-rate basis (C) those who work in a corporation with less than 10 employees (D) those who work as legal secretaries",
        "Answer": "(D) those who work as legal secretaries"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 180,
        "Question": "Section 255 (245) of the Labor Code recognizes three categories of employees, namely: managerial, supervisory, and rank-and-file.(a) Give the characteristics of each category of employees, and state whether the employees in each category may organize and form unions. Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "Managerial employees — those vested with powers or prerogatives to lay down and execute management policies and/or to hire, transfer, suspend, lay-off, recall employees (Article 219, par. m, Labor Code) Managerial employees cannot join, assist or form unions (Article 255, Labor Code). Supervisory employees — those who, in the interest of the employer, effectively recommend such managerial actions (Article 219, par. m, Labor Code) Supervisory employees are not eligible for membership in a labor organization of the rank-and-file employees but may form or join a separate labor organization of their own (Article 255, Labor Code). Rank-and-file employees — all other employees (Article 219, par. m, Labor Code) Rank-and-file employees may form or join a labor organization (Article 253, Labor Code)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 181,
        "Question": "A group of 15 regular rank-and-file employees of Bay Resort formed and registered an independent union. On hearing of this, the management called the officers to check who the union members were. It turned out that the members included the probationary staff, casuals, and the employees of the landscape contractor. The management contends that inclusion of non-regulars and employees of a contractor makes the union’s composition inappropriate and its registration invalid. Is this correct? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "NO. The management is not correct. The inclusion in a union of disqualified employees is not a ground for cancellation of union registration. The inclusion of the probationary staff, the casuals, and the employees of the landscape contractor simply makes the aforementioned employees automatically deemed removed from the union membership [Art. 245-A, Labor Code]."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 182,
        "Question": "Executive Order No. 180, which protects government employees, does NOT apply to 'high-level employees,' namely, (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "(C) confidential employees and those performing policy-determining functions."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 183,
        "Question": "Government employees may elect a union as their exclusive representative but this right is not available to (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "(C) employees of government-owned-or-conrolled corporations with original charters."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 184,
        "Question": "Distinguish the rights of managerial employees from members of a managerial staff.",
        "Answer": "Managerial employees have no collective bargaining rights because, they cannot join or form any other labor organization while officers of a managerial staff are not prohibited from joining, assisting or forming or arresting a supervisor’s union; hence, they can bargain collectively. (Art. 245, Labor Code; National Sugar Refineries Corp. vs. NLRC. 220 SCRA 452). ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: Managerial employees, under Article 212(m) of the Labor Code are vested with the prerogatives to lay down and execute management policies and/or to hire, fire, transfer, promote, lay-off and discipline employees. They are not eligible for the right to self-organization for purposes of collective bargaining. Upon the other hand, members of managerial staff, under Article 82 of the Labor Code, are not vested ’with the above-cited prerogatives. They are not entitled to overtime pay and other benefits under Book III, Title I of the Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 185,
        "Question": "1) Can an employer legally oppose the inclusion of confidential employees in the existing rank-and-file union? Explain. 2) Would your answer be the same if the confidential employees are sought to be included in the supervisory union?",
        "Answer": "1) The employer can legally oppose the inclusion of confidential employees in the existing rank-and-file union. Confidential employees are those who, in the discharge of their regular duties, hold relations of trust and confidence with the employer and are exposed to confidential matters. The inclusion of confidential employees in the bargaining unit of the rank-and-file employees would give the union access to confidential information which may become the source of undue advantage by the union over the employer. 2) The answer would be the same if confidential employees are sought to be included in the supervisory union because confidential employees, being a part of management would not qualify to Join, much less form a labor union. (Philtranco vs. BLR. 174 SCRA 388). ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: My answer would remain the same, even If the confidential employees were sought to be included in the supervisory union. Confidential employees would have the same adverse impact on the bargaining unit of supervisors: Confidential employees' access to highly sensitive information may become the source of undue advantage by the union over the employer. [Philips Industrial Development Inc., vs. National Labor Relations Commission, et.al, G.R. No. 88957, 25 June 1992)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 186,
        "Question": "Company XYZ has two recognized labor unions, one for its rank-and-file employees (RFLU), and one for supervisory employees (SELU). Of late, the company instituted a restructuring program by virtue of which A, a rank-and-file employee and officer of RFLU, was promoted to a supervisory position along with four (4) other colleagues, also active union members and/or officers. Labor Union KMJ, a rival labor union seeking recognition as the rank-and-file bargaining agent, filed a petition for cancellation of the registration of RFLU on the ground that A and her colleagues have remained to be members of RFLU. Is the petition meritorious? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. Having been promoted to supervisory positions, A and her colleagues are no longer part of the rank-and- file bargaining unit. They are deemed removed from membership of RFLU (Art. 245-A, Labor Code as amended by Rep. Act No. 9481)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 187,
        "Question": "A, an employee of XYZ Cooperative, owns 500 shares in the cooperative. He has been asked to join the XYZ Cooperative Employees Association. He seeks your advice on whether he can join the association. What advice will you give him?  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "A cannot join XYZ Cooperative Employees Association, because owning shares in XYZ Cooperative makes him a co-owner thereof. An employee-member of a cooperative cannot join a union and bargain collectively with his cooperative for an 'owner cannot bargain with himself and his co-owners' (Cooperative Rural Bank, of Davao City, Inc. v. Calleja, 165 SCRA 725, 732 ; San Jose City - Electric Service Cooperative, Inc. v. Ministry of Labor, 173 SCRA697,701- 703 )."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 188,
        "Question": "B. Assuming that A is ineligible to join the union, should the registration of Samahang Manggagawa ng Terracota be cancelled? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "NO. Rep. Act No. 9481 introduced a new provision, Art. 245-A, which provides that mixed membership is not a ground for cancellation of a union's registration, but said employees wrongfully joined are deemed removed from said union."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 189,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Answer TRUE if the statement is true, or FALSE if the statement is false. Explain your answer in not more than two (2) sentences.  [b] All confidential employees are disqualified to unionize for the purpose of collective bargaining.",
        "Answer": "False. Not all confidential employees are disqualified to unionize for the purpose of collective bargaining. Only confidential employees, who, because of the nature of their positions, have access to confidential information affecting labor-management relations as an integral part of their position are denied the right of self-organization for purpose of collective bargaining (San Miguel Corporation Supervisors v. Laguesma, 277 SCRA 370 )."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 190,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Answer TRUE if the statement is true, or FALSE if the statement is false. Explain your answer in not more than two (2) sentences.  [c] Government employees have the right to organize and join concerted mass actions without incurring administrative liability.",
        "Answer": "False. Government employees have the right to organize, but they may be held liable for engaging in concerted mass actions, it being a prohibited activity under CSC Law (E.O. 181). The right of government employees to organize is limited to the formation of unions or associations without including the right to strike. (Gesite v. CA, 444 SCRA 51 )."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 191,
        "Question": "The Confederation of Free Workers (CFW), a national labor federation, has an existing collective bargaining agreement with Tanawan Leather Company covering the Company’s rank-and-file employees who are direct members of CFW. The supervisors of the Company organized themselves into a union which they affiliated to CFW. CFW filed a petition in behalf of the supervisors for certification election. The Company opposed the petition asserting that CFW cannot represent the supervisors for collective bargaining purposes because it also represents the rank-and-file employees. You are the Med-Arbiter. Will you order the holding of a certification election? Reasons.",
        "Answer": "I will not order the holding of a certification election if the supervisors of the Company have been included by the existing CBA in the bargaining unit of the Company’s rank- and-file employees before the effectivity of Republic Act No. 6715 where the supervisors may remain, in accordance with the pertinent Rules and Regulations implementing the Labor Code. But if the supervisors are not included by the existing CBA in the bargaining unit of the Company's rank and file employees. I will order a certification election. But the Union that I will allow in the ballot of the certification election will not be CFW. the national federation which has a direct members the Company s rank and file employees. On the ballot of the certification election will instead be the local Union organized by the supervisors. The Labor Code provides that supervisory employees shall not be eligible for membership in a labor organization of the rank and file employees but may form 01 join a separate labor organization of their own. Thus. CFW of which the Company's rank and file employees are members, cannot be the Union to represent the supervisors in collective bargaining. [Atlas Lithographic Services, Inc. us. Laguesma. et al., 205 SCRA 12)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 192,
        "Question": "Lazaro, an engineer, organized a union in Garantisado Construction Corporation which has 200 employees. He secured 70 signed membership forms. He then filed a petition for a certification election. The company opposed the petition because 30 of the signatories are supervisors and, therefore, the 25% requirement was not met. If you are the Director of Labor Relations, will you approve the holding of a Certification Election. Explain your answer. (2016)",
        "Answer": "Yes, I will allow the certification election. What is required for a certification election is that at least 25 per cent of the bargaining unit must sign the petition. Since 25 percent of 200 is 50 then the fact that there were 70 signatories who signed means that it should be allowed. Note that out of the 70 signatories only the supervisors should be excluded."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 193,
        "Question": "Philhealth is a government-owned and controlled corporation employing thousands of Filipinos. Because of the desire of the employees of Philhealth to obtain better terms and conditions of employment from the government, they formed the Philhealth Employees Association (PEA) and demanded Philhealth to enter into negotiations with PEA regarding terms and conditions of employment which are not fixed by law. (2014 Bar Question) (A) Are the employees of Philhealth allowed to self-organize and form PEA and thereafter demand Philhealth to enter into negotiations with PEA for better terms and conditions of employment? (B) In case of unresolved grievances, can PEA resort to strikes, walkouts, and other temporary work stoppages to pressure the government to accede to their demands?",
        "Answer": "(A) Yes. Employees of Philhealth are allowed to self-organize under Section 8, Article III and Section 3, Article XIII of the Constitution which recognize the rights of all workers to self-organization. They cannot demand, however, for better terms and conditions of employment for the same are fixed by law (Art. 244, Labor Code), besides, their salaries are standardized by Congress (Art. 276, Labor Code). (B) No. Since the terms and conditions of government employment are fixed by law, government workers cannot use the same weapons employed by workers in the private sector to secure concessions from their employers. (Blaquera vs. Alcala, G.R. Nos. 109406, 110642, 111494, 112056, 119597, September 11, 1998)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 194,
        "Question": "What is the rule on the equity of the incumbent? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The Equity of the Incumbent rule has it that all existing federations or national unions, possessing all qualifications of an LLO and none of the grounds for CR cancellation, shall continue to maintain their existing affiliates regardless of their location or industry to which they belong. In case of dissociation, affiliates are not required to observe the one union-one industry rule."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 195,
        "Question": "George is an American who is working as a consultant for a local IT company. The company has a union and George wants to support the union. How far can George go in terms of his support for the union? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "George, as a general rule, is prohibited by Art. 270(a) of the Labor Code from giving any donation, grant or other form of assistance, in cash or in kind, directly or indirectly to the Union. He can give a support only upon prior permission from the Secretary of Labor relative to 'Trade Union activities' as defined in said law. George, in addition to his alien employment permit, must first prove that the country whereof he is a national recognizes the right of Filipinos working therein to organize. Under these conditions, he is allowed to support the existing union by joining it as to increase its membership."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 196,
        "Question": "The modes of determining the exclusive bargaining agent of the employees in a business are: (a) voluntary recognition; (b) certification election; and (c) consent election. Explain how they differ from one another. (4%) (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Voluntary Recognition: An employer may voluntarily recognize the representation status of a labor union if the establishment is unorganized and has only one legitimate labor organization. Such voluntary recognition, accompanied by supporting documents, should be submitted to the Regional Office, which issued the labor union's certificate of registration. Certification Election: It refers to the process of determining the sole and exclusive bargaining agent of the employees in an appropriate bargaining unit. It shall not be barred by a statement where a contract has been given, or a stipulation that only one union or a specific union shall represent the employees. Consent Election: It refers to the election voluntarily agreed upon by the parties, with or without the intervention of the Department of Labor and Employment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 197,
        "Question": "The modes of determining the exclusive bargaining agent of the employees in a business are: 1. voluntary recognition 2. certification election 3. consent election Explain briefly how they differ from one another.  (2012 BAR)",
        "Answer": "'Voluntary Recognition' refers to the process by which a legitimate labor union is recognized by the employer as the exclusive bargaining representative or agent in a bargaining unit. Sec. 1, (bbb), Rule 1, Book V (Omnibus Rules Implmenting the Labor Code). 'Certification Election' refers to the process of determining the sole and exclusive bargaining agent of the employees in an appropriate bargaining unit through a secret ballot. (Art. 256, Labor Code). 'Consent Election' refers to the election voluntarily agreed upon by the parties to determine the issue of majority representation of all the workers in the appropriate collective bargaining unit. (Sec. 1 (g), Rule I, Book V, Omnibus Rules Implementing the Labor Code). Another Suggested Answer: 1. Voluntary Recognition is possible only in unorganized establishments where there is only one legitimate labor organization and the employer voluntarily recognize the representation status of such a union; whereas, 2. Certification Election is conducted when there are two or more unions that are seeking to represent the employees in a bargaining unit. 3. Consent Election is voluntarily agreed upon by the parties to determine the issue of majority representation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 198,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of a certification election?",
        "Answer": "The purpose of a certification election is to determine the labor organization which shall be the exclusive bargaining agent of the employees of an appropriate collective bargaining unit. A certification election may also determine whether or not the employees wish to have a collective bargaining representative because in a certification election, employees can vole for 'no union. Preliminarily. through a certification election, the members of an appropriate collective bargaining unit may also be authoritatively determined. (Arts. 255. 256, 257. Labor Code)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 199,
        "Question": "Liwayway Glass had 600 rank-and-file employees. Three rival unions A, B, and C ‒ participated in the certification elections ordered by the Med-Arbiter. 500 employees voted. The unions obtained the following votes: A-200; B-150; C-50; 90 employees voted 'no union'; and 10 were segregated votes. Out of the segregated votes, four (4) were cast by probationary employees and six (6) were cast by dismissed employees whose respective cases are still on appeal. (2014 Bar Question) (A) Should the votes of the probationary and dismissed employees be counted? (B) Was there a valid election? (C) Should Union A be declared the winner? (D) Suppose the election is declared invalid, which of the contending unions should represent the rank-and-file employees? (E) Suppose that in the election, the unions obtained the following votes: A-250; B-150; C-50; 40 voted 'no union'; and 10 were segregated votes. Should Union A be certified as the bargaining representative?",
        "Answer": "(A) Yes. All employees who are included in the appropriate bargaining unit, irrespective of their employment status, are eligible to vote in a certification election. The votes of the dismissed employees whose cases are pending on appeal shall be likewise counted, if the vote is necessary to determine the winner. In this case, there are 410 valid votes, so 206 votes are necessary to win. If Union A won, the vote of the 6 dismissed employees should be tallied. (B) Yes. To have a valid election, at least a majority of all eligible voters in the unit must have cast their votes (Article 256, now Article 266, of the Labor Code). In the instant case, 500 out of 600 rank-and-file employees voted. (C) No. The Labor Code provides that the Labor Union receiving the majority of the valid votes cast shall be certified as the exclusive bargaining agent of all the workers in the unit (Article 256, now Article 266, of the Labor Code). Here, the number of valid votes cast is 490; thus, the winning union should receive at least 246 votes. Union A only received 200 votes. (D) None of them should represent the rank-and-file employees (Article 255, now Article 265, of the Labor Code). (E) Yes. The Labor Code provides that the Labor Union receiving the majority of the valid votes cast shall be certified as the exclusive bargaining agent of all the workers in the unit (Article 256, now Article 266, of the Labor Code). Here, the number of valid votes cast is 490. Thus, the winning union should receive at least 246 votes; Union A received 250 votes."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 200,
        "Question": "Samahang East Gate Enterprises (SEGE) is a labor organization composed of the rank-and-file employees of East Gate Enterprises (EGE), the leading manufacturer of all types of gloves and aprons. EGE was later requested by SEGE to bargain collectively for better terms and conditions of employment of all the rank-and-file employees of EGE. Consequently, EGE filed a petition for certification election before the Bureau of Labor Relations (BLR). During the proceedings, EGE insisted that it should participate in the certification process. EGE reasoned that since it was the one who filed the petition and considering that the employees concerned were its own rank-and-file employees, it should be allowed to take an active part in the certification process. Is the contention of EGE proper? Explain. (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. Under Article 258-A of the Labor Code, an employer is a mere bystander in certification elections, whether the petition for certification election is filed by said employer or a legitimate labor organization. The employer shall not be considered a party thereto with a concomitant right to oppose a petition for certification election."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 201,
        "Question": "The PMG Stevedoring Company, which is engaged in the loading and unloading of cargo vessels at the Manila North Harbor. has 500 regular employees. On January 2. 1989. the 'AH' Labor Organization filed with the DOLE National Capital Region a petition for certification election, claiming to represent the 100 janitors, 80 clerks and all the other 320 regular employees of PMG. The petition did not, however, state the number of its members in the bargaining unit. After hearing, the med-arbiter ordered a certification election in the company-wide unit. Not satisfied therewith, the company elevated the order to the Secretary of Labor and Employment. If you were the Secretary of Labor and Employment, how will you decide this case? Give your reasons.",
        "Answer": "As Secretary of Labor and Employment, I will affirm the order for a certification election made by the Med Arbiter. But I will amend the order. Instead of a certification election in a company wide unit, I will order a certification election only for a bargaining unit composed of rank and file employees, or only for a bargaining unit composed of supervisory employees, in whichever bargaining unit are found the members of the petitioning labor organization. The order for a certification election is proper even if the petition for certification election filed by AH Labor Organization is not supported by at least 25% of the employees of the appropriate collective bargaining unit. The petition for certification election is filed in an unorganized establish-ment there being, as yet. no bargaining agent in PMG Stevedoring Company. A petition for certification election in an unorganized establishment does not require the consent of at least 25% of all the employees in the bargaining unit (Art. 257. Labor Code). This is a requirement only for petitions filed in an organized establishment. (Art. 256, Labor Code) But the bargaining unit cannot be company wide. Rep. Act No. 6715, in reaffirming the right of supervisory employees to form a union, provides that they can only be members of unions whose members are all supervisory employees. This restriction means that, unlike the situation before Rep. Act No. 6715. supervisory employees and rank and file employees could no longer belong to one union. Thus, as a result, a bargaining unit could no longer be composed of rank and file employees and supervisor employees. A POINT TO CONSIDER: A bar examinee may. however, assume that the reference to the bargaining unit being a companywide unit means either a companywide unit of all rank and file employees or a companywide unit of all supervisory employees. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: As Secretary, I would affirm the order of the med- arbiter. There is no bar to the election, and the employees are entitled to a speedy determination of their bargaining representative so that they could exercise their right to bargain collectively."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 202,
        "Question": "The constituency of the bargaining unit in Complex Electronics Corporation consisted of 800 employees. Four unions - A, B, C. and D - vied to represent the employees for collective bargaining purposes. In a certification election ordered by the Med-Arbiter, 700 employees voted. Union A obtained 200 votes; Union B, 150 votes, Union C, 70 votes; and Union D, 30 votes. 250 employees voted no union.' a) Was there a valid election? Why? b) Which union should be certified as bargaining representative of tire employees? Why? c) Should a new election be conducted with all the four unions participating? Reasons.",
        "Answer": "a) Yes, There was a valid election. The Labor Code requires that for a certification election to be valid, at least a majority of all eligible voters in the unit must have cast their votes. (Article 256, Labor Code) Here, the number of eligible voters was 800. Seven hundred (700) or more than a majority voted. Thus, the election was valid. b) No union could be certified as bargaining representative of employees. To be certified, a labor union should receive a majority of valid votes cast of at least a majority of the 800 votes cast which should be 401 votes. (Article 256, Labor Code) The union obtaining the highest number of votes is Union A. It obtained only 200 votes, short of the majority by 201 votes. c) A new election should be conducted, but the Labor Code provides that it should be an election not at all the four unions who participated in the election but a run-off election where only the labor unions receiving the two highest numbers of votes will participate. This run-off election can be held because in the earlier election, the total number of votes for all the contending unions was at least fifty percent (50%) of the number of votes cast. Here. 450 votes or more than a majority of the 800 votes cast, were votes for all contending unions. (Article 256, Labor Code)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 203,
        "Question": "Suppose in the election. Union A obtained 300 votes. Union B, 30 votes. Union C. 10 votes and Union D, no votes and 360 voted no union. Should Union A be certified as bargaining representative? Reasons.",
        "Answer": "No union should be certified. The winning union should have received a majority of the valid votes cast, which is 371 votes (300+30+10+360=700 valid votes cast. Majority is 351). Union A received only 300 votes, which is less than the majority. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: No union should be certified. No union got a majority of the valid votes cast, which is 224 votes [Vi of 450 plus 1). The Labor Code (in Art. 256) provides that a union, to be certified as the exclusive bargaining agent of the workers in a bargaining unit, should receive a majority of the valid votes cast."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 204,
        "Question": "Distinguish clearly but briefly between: x x x x x x x x x x x x Consent election and certification election. Social security and union security.",
        "Answer": "A certification election and a consent election are both elections held to determine through secret ballot the sole and exclusive representative of the employees in an appropriate bargaining unit for the purpose of collective bargaining or negotiations. There is this difference, however. A certification election is ordered by the Department of Labor and Employment while a consent election is voluntarily agreed upon by the parties, with or without the intervention of the Social Security is the protection given by social insurance programs such as the programs of the SSS, GSIS and PHIC undertaken pursuant to their respective charters, including the employees compensation program provided for in the Labor Code. The aforesaid programs provide income benefits and/or medical care when the contingency occurs. Union security, on the other hand, is the right of a certified labor union to enter into a collective bargaining agreement which requires as a condition of employment that a workers is, or remains a member in good standing of the union."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 205,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Answer TRUE if the statement is true, or FALSE if the statement is false. Explain your answer in not more than two (2) sentences.  [d] In the law on labor relations, the substitutionary doctrine prohibits a new collective bargaining agent from repudiating an existing collective bargaining agreement. (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "True. The existing collective bargaining agreement (in full force and effect) must be honored by a new exclusive bargaining representative because of the policy of stability in labor relations between an employer and the workers."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 206,
        "Question": "Upon the expiration of the first three (3) years of their CBA, the union and the company commenced negotiations. The union demanded that the company continue to honor their 30-day union leave benefit under the CBA. The company refused on the ground that the CBA had already expired, and the union had already consumed their union leave under the CBA. Who is correct? (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "(B) The company is correct because the union has already consumed the allotted union leave under the expired CBA. SUGGESTED ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: (D) Basis: Article 259 (formerly Article 253) of the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 207,
        "Question": "ABC company and U labor union have been negotiating for a new Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) but failed to agree on certain economic provisions of the existing agreement. In the meantime, the existing CBA expired. The company thereafter refused to pay the employees their midyear bonus, saying that the CBA which provided for the grant of midyear bonus to all company employees had already expired. Are the employees entitled to be paid their midyear bonus? Explain your answer.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Yes. The CBA merely serves as the working agreement between the employer and the employee and the grant of midyear bonus is already an established practice and forms part of the perquisites of the employees. Hence, pending the conclusion of a new agreement, the midyear bonus should be paid."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 208,
        "Question": "Is management’s withdrawal of the fringe benefits valid? Reasons.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "No. Pending renewal of the CBA, the parties are bound to keep the status quo and to treat the terms and conditions embodied therein still in full force and effect, until a new agreement is reached by the union and management. This is part and parcel of the duty to bargain collectively in good faith under Article 253, the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 209,
        "Question": "What, if any, is the maximum term of a collective bargaining agreement under R.A. 6715? Company America and the union entered into a five (5) year collective bargaining agreement (CBA). Three (3) years thereafter, the Company received a demand letter from the union for renegotiation of the terms and conditions of the CBA on the ground that the cost of living and prices of the essential commodities have gone up by 30% since the CBA was concluded.",
        "Answer": "The maximum term is five (5) years as to the representation aspect. All other provisions of a CBA shall only have a maximum term of three (3) years. The demand letter of the union for renegotiation of the economic terms of the CBA is valid and is given to avoid any labor dispute that would adversely affect the economy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 210,
        "Question": "A. XYZ Company and Mr. AB, a terminated employee who also happens to be the President of XYZ Employees Union, agree in writing to submit Mr. AB's illegal dismissal case to voluntary arbitration. Is this agreement a valid one? (2015 Bar Question) B. XYZ Company and XYZ Employees Union (XYZEU) reach a deadlock in their negotiation for a new collective bargaining agreement (CBA). XYZEU files a notice of strike; XYZ Company proposes to XYZEU that the deadlock be submitted instead to voluntary arbitration. If you are counsel for XYZEU, what advice would you give the union as to the: (1) propriety of the request of XYZ Company, and (2) the relative advantages/disadvantages between voluntary arbitration and compulsory arbitration? (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The agreement is valid because the preferred mode of settling labor disputes is through voluntary modes, like voluntary arbitration. The agreement is consistent with Sec. 3, Art. XIII of the Constitution. Moreover, Art. 262 of the Labor Code authorizes a voluntary arbitrator to hear and decide by agreement of the parties, all other labor disputes. (1) As counsel, I will advise the union to accede to the request of the company. Besides being the constitutionally preferred mode of dispute settlement, voluntary arbitration is less adversarial and more expeditious. (2) The advantages of voluntary arbitration are: (a) faster, cheaper and easier; (b) Voluntary Arbitrator/s, unlike Labor Arbiters, cannot be compelled to render decision in thirty (30) days from submission of case for decision, as such period is only advisory in character."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 211,
        "Question": "Which mode of dispute settlement is the fastest way of resolving disputes? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "a. Arbitration;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 212,
        "Question": "The parties to a labor dispute can validly submit to voluntary arbitration _________. (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "(A) any disputed issue they may agree to voluntarily arbitrate"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 213,
        "Question": "Company and Triple-X Union, the certified bargaining agent of rank-and-file employees, entered into a Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) effective for the period January 1, 2002 to December 31, 2007. For the 4th and 5th years of the CBA, the significant improvements in wages and other benefits obtained by the Union were: 1) Salary increases of PI,000 and PI,200 monthly, effective January 1, 2006 and January 1, 2007, respectively; 2) Vacation Leave and Sick Leave were increased from 12 days to 15 days annually; and 3) An additional rice subsidy of P300.00 monthly. In the 3rd year of the CBA, the Company, contending that the salary and other economic benefits are too high and no longer competitive, proposed to the Union the following changes: a) The salary increase of PI,200 monthly for the 5th year of the CBA be deleted; b) The vacation leave and sick leave be decreased to 10 days annually; and c) The monthly rice subsidy be deleted. [d] If you were the lawyer for the union, what legal recourse or action would you advise? Reasons. ",
        "Answer": "I would recommend the filing of an unfair labor practice case against the employer for violating the duty to bargain collectively under Article 248(g) of the Labor Code. This arbitration case also institutes the 'deadlock bar' that shall prevent any other union from filing a petition for certification election. ANOTHER SUGGESTED ANSWER: I will advice the Union to continue negotiations with the aid of the NCMB (Art. 250, Labor Code), and to file a complaint for unfair labor practice, i.e., violation of an economic provision, gross and serious in character under Articles 248(i) and Art. 261 of the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 214,
        "Question": "When was the 'freedom period' referred to in the foregoing narration of facts? Explain.  (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "The freedom period or the time within which a petition for certification election to challenge the incumbent collective bargaining agent may be filed is from 60 days before the expiry date of the CBA."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 215,
        "Question": "What are the liabilities of Dana Films and MMFF to the dismissed employees, if any?  (2012 BAR)",
        "Answer": "Dana Films is obliged (1) to reinstate the illegally dismissed employees to their former positions without reduction in rank, seniority and salary; and (2) to jointly and severally pay the dismissed employees backwages, without any reduction in pay or qualification. [Amada Rice v. NLRC, G.R. No. 68147, June 30, 1988]."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 216,
        "Question": "Distinguish between a closed shop clause and a maintenance of membership clause. (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "In a 'closed shop' clause, all employees are required to be members of the union at the time of hiring. They too must remain members of good standing during the period of employment as a condition of continued employment. Maintenance of membership clause, on the other hand, requires all employees who are union members at the time of the execution of the CBA to maintain their membership of good standing, as a condition of continued employment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 217,
        "Question": "Distinguish between union dues and agency fees. (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Union dues are union funds paid by union members, normally through check-off by the employer on the basis of an individual written authorization duly signed by the employees pursuant to Art. 241 (o) of the Labor Code. Agency fee, on the other hand, is a reasonable fee equivalent to the dues and other fees paid by members of the recognized collective bargaining agent. Art. 248(e) of the Labor Code mandates that only non-union members who accept the benefits under the CBA may be assessed agency fees. Their check-off authorization is not required."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 218,
        "Question": "A is employed by XYZ Company where XYZ Employees Union (XYZ-EU) is the recognized exclusive bargaining agent. Although A is a member of rival union XYR-MU, he receives the benefits under the CBA that XYZ-EU had negotiated with the company. XYZ-EU assessed A a fee equivalent to the dues and other fees paid by its members but A insists that he has no obligation to pay said dues and fees because he is not a member of XYZ-EU and he has not issued an authorization to allow the collection. Explain whether his claim is meritorious.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "NO. The fee exacted from A takes the form of an AGENCY FEE. This is sanctioned by Article 248 (e) of the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 219,
        "Question": "Differentiate 'surface bargaining' from 'blue-sky bargaining'.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "(1) SURFACE BARGAINING is defined as 'going through the motions of negotiating' without any legal intent to reach an agreement. The determination of whether a party has engaged in unlawful surface bargaining is a question of the intent of the party in question, which can only be inferred from the totality of the challenged party’s conduct both at and away from the bargaining table. It involves the question of whether an employer’s conduct demonstrates an unwillingness to bargain in good faith or is merely hard bargaining (Standard Chartered Bank Employees Union (NUBE)v. Confesor, 432 SCRA 308 ). (2) BLUE-SKY BARGAINING is defined as 'unrealistic and unreasonable demands in negotiations by either or both labor and management, where neither concedes anything and demands the impossible' (Standard Chartered Bank Employees Union (NUBE) v. Confesor, supra.)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 220,
        "Question": "The recreation fund of the labor union is regularly supported by the employer by way of regular contributions. The said fund, without any assistance given by the employer, is used for refreshment and other expenses of the labor union whenever the employees go on a picnic, on an excursion, or hold a Christmas party. Is the employer liable for unfair labor practice under Article 248(d) of the Labor Code? Explain your answer.",
        "Answer": "No. If the contributions of the employer benefit all the employees and there is no employee discriminated against, there is no unfair labor practice. The contributions may be considered a fringe benefit given by the employer. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: If the regular contributions are pursuant to a CBA provision, there is no unfair labor practice. If not pursuant to a CBA violation, the assistance may constitute an unfair labor practice. ANOTHER ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: If Art. 248(d) is strictly applied, the giving of money by the employer to the recreation fund of the labor union is an unfair labor practice because said Article considers as an unfair labor practice 'the giving of financial or other support to it (meaning a union) or to its organizers or officers.' The Article does not provide for a situation where such giving is not an unfair labor practice."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 221,
        "Question": "The management and Union X in Atisan Mining entered into a CBA for 1997 to 2001. After 6 months, a majority of the members of Union X formed Union Y and sought management recognition. The latter responded by not dealing with either union. But, when the CBA’s economic provisions had to be renegotiated towards the end of the term of the CBA, the management chose to negotiate with Union Y, the newer union. Thus, Union X which negotiated the existing CBA charged the company with unfair labor practice (ULP). The company argued that it committed no unfair labor practice since the supposed violation had nothing to do with economic provisions of the CBA. Is the management right? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "No. The duty to bargain collectively is not merely confined to economic provisions but to all terms and conditions of employment. The management should negotiate with Union X, the existing certified bargaining agent, especially on the economic provisions of the existing CBA because Article 253 of the Labor Code mandates the continuance of the terms and conditions in the CBA until a new one is executed."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 222,
        "Question": "Unions 'A' and 'B' are competing with one another to organize the employees of Ocean Supermart. Inc. It was an uncertain contest until the President of Ocean Supermart issued a written statement expressing the hope that the employees refrain from joining a union but in the event they should decide to do so, stating his preference for Union 'A'. In the certification election Union 'B' lost. Is there an unfair labor practice? Reasons.",
        "Answer": "Ocean Supermart was guilty of unfair labor practice. The Labor Code (in Art. 248) provides that it is unfair labor practice for an employer 'To interfere with, restrain or coerce employees in the exercise of their right to self-organization' and 'for an employer to initiate, dominate, assist or otherwise interfere in the formation or administration of any labor organization, including the giving of financial or other support to it or its organizations or supporters.' In the question given, Ocean Supermart issued a written statement expressing the hope that the employees refrain from joining a union. It also express a preference for Union 'A'. These statements could be considered interference with the exercise by employees by the right to self-organize. Giving support to a particular union is an act of company unionism therefore, was an unfair labor practice."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true in unfair labor practices committed by an employer? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "a. They are crimes punishable with a fine of not less than P1,000.00 nor more than P10,000.00 and/or imprisonment of not less than three months nor more than one (1) year."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 224,
        "Question": "When there is no recognized collective bargaining agent, can a legitimate labor organization validly declare a strike against the employer? (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "(C) Yes, because the employees are still allowed to exercise their right to concerted activities under the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 225,
        "Question": "What do you understand by the 'improved offer balloting?'",
        "Answer": "A strike may be an economic strike, namely, it is a strike caused by a deadlock at the bargaining table. A deadlock may arise because the offer of the employer, e.g., its offer of a 20% across-the-board increase in wages and salaries, was not accepted by the Union who wanted a 50% increase. After considering the matter, the employer may improve its offer, e.g. it offers a 35% increase. This improved offer of the employer may be submitted to the union members on or before the 30th day of the strike. The secret balloting that will determine whether a majority of the union members accept the improved offer of the employer is the so-called ''improved offer balloting. In case it is a lockout, and not a strike, what may be the subject matter of a secret balloting, this lime among the members of the Board of Directors of the employer, may be the reduced offer of the union, i.e., instead of asking for 50% across the board increase in wages and salaries, it may reduce its demand to 25 % ."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 226,
        "Question": "On May 24, 1989, the UKM urged its member-unions to join a 'Welga ng Bayan' in support of its efforts to pressure Congress to increase the daily minimum wage. Union 'X' is a member of the UKM and represents all the rank and file employees of the Puritan Mining Company. Following the call for a nationwide strike, Union 'X' staged a strike and put up a picket the following day. As a result, the company’s operations were paralyzed although company officials and supervisory employees were allowed ingress and egress to and from the company premises. The picket was likewise peaceful. On May 28, 1989, the UKM leadership announced the end of the 'Welga ng Bayan.' Union 'X' immediately lifted its picket and its members went back to work. The company sought our legal advice on the legality of the strike and the liability, if any, of the union officers and the participating members. What is your opinion? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The strike is illegal. A strike is illegal if it is not based on a valid ground, such as a labor dispute. The cause of the strike, namely, the desire of UKM to pressure Congress to increase the minimum wage is not a labor dispute. The liability of the union officers is termination of their employment. The striking members shall not be terminated except if they participated in the commission of illegal acts during the strike."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 227,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a valid reason for a strike? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "d. Demand for regularization of employees."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 228,
        "Question": "In response to Company X’s unfair labor practices, a union officer instructed its members to stop working and walk out of the company premises. After three (3) hours, they voluntarily returned to work. Was there a strike and was it a valid activity? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "b. Yes, it was a strike; No, it was not a valid activity;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 229,
        "Question": "As a result of a bargaining deadlock between Lazo Corporation and Lazo Employees Union, the latter staged a strike. During the strike, several employees committed illegal acts. Eventually, its members informed the company of their intention to return to work. (2014 Bar Question) (A) Can Lazo Corporation refuse to admit the strikers? (B) Assuming the company admits the strikers, can it later on dismiss the employees who committed illegal acts during the strike?",
        "Answer": "(A) No. The Commission of illegal acts during a strike does not automatically bring about loss of employment status. Due process must be observed by the employer before any dismissal can be made. {Stanford Marketing Corp. v. Julian, 423 SCRA 633 (2004]). (B) Yes. The Labor Code explicitly provides for loss of employment status of 'ANY WORKER' or union officer who knowingly participates in the commission of illegal acts during a strike."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 230,
        "Question": "Were the temporary reassignment and payroll reinstatement valid?",
        "Answer": "No. The temporary re-assignment and payroll rein- statement are not valid. According to the Labor Code, when the Secretary of Labor assumes Jurisdiction, such assumption has the effect of automatically enjoining the strike that is taking place and all striking employees shall immediately return to work as the employer shall immediately resume operations and readmit all workers under the same terms and conditions prevailing before the strikes. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: The temporary re-assignment and payroll reinstatement are valid, if they are made in good faith, and are not for the purpose of discouraging membership in the union. It is the prerogative of the management to assign its employees to where the management believes their services could be best utilized. As for the payroll reinstatement, it is valid if there is a valid reason to prevent the workers placed or payroll reinstatement from actually returning to work, like a valid fear that they will sabotage equipment in the company,"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 231,
        "Question": "Several employees and members of Union A were terminated by Western Phone Co. on the ground of redundancy. After complying with the necessary requirements, the Union staged a strike and picketed the premises of the company. The management then filed a petition for the Secretary of Labor and Employment to assume jurisdiction over the dispute. Without the benefit of a hearing, the Secretary issued an Order to assume jurisdiction and for the parties to revert to the status quo ante litem. (2010 Bar Question) A. Was the order to assume jurisdiction legal? Explain.  B. Was the order to revert to the status quo ante litem legal? ",
        "Answer": "A. YES. The Secretary of Labor and Employment has plenary power to assume jurisdiction under Article 263(g) of the Labor Code. When in his opinion, there exists a labor dispute causing or likely to cause a strike or lockout in an industry indispensable to the national interest, he may assume jurisdiction over the dispute or certify the same to the NLRC for compulsory arbitration. B. NO. The general rule is that the parties should revert to the status quo ante litem, which means the time before the compulsory arbitration was filed. In this case, the strike already started. Thus, the Secretary should have issued a return to work order."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 232,
        "Question": "As trial judge, will you issue an injunction against ABC and the workers? Explain.",
        "Answer": "As trial judge, I will not issue an injunction against ABC and the workers. The acts of ABC and the workers, namely, the workers joining ABC said workers demanding that they be made regular employees, ABC filing a notice of strike with the Department of Labor and Employment, all these acts brought about a labor dispute which is not within the jurisdiction of the Regional Trial Court. The fact that the Company is asserting that the workers are not employees of the Company does not make the case between the Company, on one hand, and ABC and the workers, on the other hand, not a labor dispute. The truth cr falsity of the assertion of the Company is a matter that is within a Labor Arbiter, not a Regional Trial Court. to decide. (San Miguel Corp. Employees Union-PTGWO-vs. Bersamina, 186 SCRA 496) If an injunction is proper, it is the National. Labor Relations Commission that can enjoin ABC and the workers from doing any unlawful act. The Labor Code (in Article 254) is very clear: No temporary or permanent injunction or restraining order involving or growing out of a labor dispute shall be enjoined by any court or other entity except by the NLRC under Articles 218 and under 264."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 233,
        "Question": "State the jurisdiction of the Voluntary Arbitrator, or Panel of Voluntary Arbitrators in labor disputes? (4%) (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "Under Articles 274 and 275 of the Labor Code, as re-numbered, the jurisdiction of Voluntary Arbitrators or Panel of Voluntary Arbitrators are: (a) original and exclusive jurisdiction to hear and decide all unresolved grievances arising from the interpretation or implementation of the Collective Bargaining Agreement (Article 274); (b) those arising from the interpretation or enforcement of company personnel policies (Id.); (c) upon agreement of the parties, jurisdiction to hear and decide all other labor disputes including unfair labor practices and bargaining deadlocks (Article 275)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 234,
        "Question": "Pedring, Daniel, and Paul were employees of Delibakery who resigned from their jobs but wanted to file money claims for unpaid wages and 13th month pay. Pedring’s claim totals P20,000.00, Daniel’s P3,000.00, and Paul’s P22,000.00. Daniel changed his mind and now also wants reinstatement because he resigned only upon the instigation of Pedring and Paul. Where should they file their claims? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "(C) With a labor arbiter for all three complainants."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 235,
        "Question": "Quiel, a househelper in the Wilson household since 2006, resigned from his job for several reasons. One reason was the daily 12-hour workday without any rest day. When he left his job he had unpaid wages totaling P13,500.00 which his employer refused to pay. He wants to claim this amount though he is not interested in getting back his job. Where should he file his claim? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "(C) He should file his claim exceeding P5,000.00 with the office of the labor arbiters, the regional arbitrators representing the NLRC."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 236,
        "Question": "As the lawyer of Mr. Excelente, state the nature of your action or complaint to be filed against the university, the proper body or court before which it may be filed, the laws to be invoked, and the facts or evidence to be adduced.",
        "Answer": "As lawyer of Mr. Excelente, I will file a complaint questioning the legality of his dismissal. I will file the complaint with the Labor Arbiter in the Regional Arbitration Branch of the NLRC having jurisdiction over the place where Mr. Excelente works. I will invoke the provisions of the Labor Code which are found in its Book VI that guarantee the right of workers to security of tenure. I will adduce facts or evidence that will disprove the allegations of the University President that have been given as reasons for dismissing Mr. Excelente. The fact that he had served the University for twenty five years, was well known in his field and has received many awards should disprove the allegation of gross incompetence. I will content that the alteration over teaching loads of professors is not tantamount to insubordination and dereliction of duty."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 237,
        "Question": "May the University President be impleaded as co-respondent? If so, what will be the nature of his liability?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the University President may be impleaded as co-respondent. If he acted in bad faith, he may be held jointly and severally liable with the University for the backwages of Mr. Excelente."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 238,
        "Question": "Is a termination dispute a grievable issue? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "c) No, once there’s actual termination, the issue is cognizable by a Labor Arbiter [Art. 217 (a), Labor Code; San Miguel Corporation vs. NLRC, G.R. No. 108001, March 15, 1996]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 239,
        "Question": "The jurisdiction of the National Labor Relations Commission does not include: (2014 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "(B) exclusive appellate jurisdiction over all cases decided by Regional Directors or hearing officers involving the recovery of wages and other monetary claims and benefits arising from employer-employee relations where the aggregate money claim of each does not exceed five thousand pesos (Php5,000)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 240,
        "Question": "A neighbor’s gardener comes to you and asks for help because his employer withheld his salary for two (2) months amounting to P4,000.00. Where will you advise him to file his complaint? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "b. DOLE Regional Director [Art. 129, Labor Code]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 241,
        "Question": "Who has jurisdiction over a money claim instituted by an overseas Filipino workers? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "a) Labor Arbiter [Sec. 10, Art. 8042]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 242,
        "Question": "The appeal to the NLRC may be entertained only on any of the following grounds, except: (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "c. If made purely on questions of fact and law;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 243,
        "Question": "The Secretary of Labor and Employment or his duly authorized representative, including labor regulations officers, shall have access to employer's records and premises during work hours. Why is this statement an inaccurate statement of the law? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "(A) The law allows access anytime of the day or night, not only during work hours."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 244,
        "Question": "A party is prohibited from bringing up an issue on appeal, if: (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "(D) they appear in cases involving an amount of less than Php5,000"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 245,
        "Question": "Jim is the holder of a certificate of public convenience for a jeepney. He entered into a 'lease contract' with Nick for the latter to drive the jeepney for 12 hours daily on a fix 'rental' of P1,500.00. The lease contract also stipulated that Nick should observe the rules and regulations of Jim respecting the maintenance of the jeepney and dealing with passengers. Jim filed a motion to dismiss the complaint for lack of jurisdiction as the agreement between him and Nick is a lease contract. Rule on the motion and explain. (2016)",
        "Answer": "Jim's Motion to Dismiss must be denied. Although Jim and Nick called their contract as a lease, it is actually a contract of employment, and the rentals that Nick must pay to Jim is actually a boundary. Martinez v. National Labor Relations Commission (G.R. No. 117495, May 29,1997) teaches that jeepney owners/operators exercise control over jeepney drivers. The fact that the drivers do not receive fixed wages but get only that in excess of the so-called 'boundary' is not a circumstance which would negate the existence of employer-employee relationship."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 246,
        "Question": "May the NLRC or the courts take jurisdictional cognizance over compromise agreements/ settlements involving labor matters?",
        "Answer": "No. Any compromise agreement, including those involving labor standards laws, voluntary agreed upon by the parties with the assistance of the Bureau or the regional office of the Department of Labor, shall be final and binding upon the parties. The National Labor Relations Commission or any court shall not assume jurisdiction over issues involved therein except in case of non- compliance thereof or if there is prima facie evidence that the settlement was obtained through fraud, misrepresentation, or coercion. (Art. 227, Labor Code)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 247,
        "Question": "Jose Lovina had been member of the board of directors and Executive Vice President of San Jose Corporation for 12 years. In 2008, the San Jose stockholders did not elect him to the board of directors nor did the board reappoint him as Executive Vice President. He filed an illegal dismissal complaint with a Labor Arbiter. Contending that the Labor Arbiter had no jurisdiction over the case since Lovina was not an employee, the company filed a motion to dismiss. Should the motion be granted? (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "(D) Yes, jurisdiction lies with the regular courts since the complainant was a corporate officer."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 248,
        "Question": "Philippine News Network (PNN) engages the services of Anya, a prominent news anchor from a rival station, National News Network (NNN). NNN objects to the transfer of Anya claiming that she is barred from working in a competing company for a period of three years from the expiration of her contract. Anya proceeds to sign with PNN which then asks her to anchor their nightly newscast. NNN sues Anya and PNN before the National Labor Relations Commission (NLRC), asking for a labor injunction. Anya and PNN object claiming that it is a matter cognizable by a regular court and not the NLRC. (a) Is NNN's remedy correct? Why or why not? (2015 Bar Question) (b) What are the grounds for a labor injunction to issue? (2015 Bar Question) (c) Distinguish the jurisdiction of a Labor Arbiter from that of the NLRC. (2015 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "(a) No. The NLRC has no jurisdiction. The case is a civil dispute. The issue revolves around the enforcement of the exclusivity clause in the contract, which is a matter of civil relations. (b) A labor injunction may issue when the matter involves a labor dispute, and is necessary to protect the interest of the complaining party, taking into account the irreparable damage or injury to the moving party. In case of illegal dismissal, the Labor Arbiter has the power to issue a restraining order or writ of injunction, where the reinstatement aspect of the case is involved. (c) The Labor Arbiter has jurisdiction over all original claims listed in Art. 224 (Art. 217). The NLRC has exclusive appellate jurisdiction over all cases decided by the Labor Arbiter and the DOLE Regional Director. As to the power to issue a labor injunction, the NLRC can issue an injunctive writ. On the other hand, the Labor Arbiter cannot issue an injunctive writ."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 249,
        "Question": "An employee filed a complaint against his employer before the National Labor Relations Commission (NLRC). The labor arbiter decided the case in favor of the employee. The employer received a copy of the decision on April 10. 1984. April 20 being a Good Friday and the following Saturday having been declared a non-working public holiday by the President, the employer filed his appeal with the NLRC from the said decision on April 23. 1984. (1) Was the appeal filed on time? Explain your reason. (2) Assuming the decision of the labor arbiter is affirmed by the NLRC. what is the recourse of the employer? State the nature of the action, the court which has jurisdiction over the action, and the period within which the same must be filed.",
        "Answer": "(1) The appeal was filed on time. The Supreme Court has ruled that in the counting of the ten day period within which to file an appeal, if the tenth day is a holiday, then the appeal may be filed on the day after said holiday. But if the day after said holiday is also a non-working public holiday as in the case in the question, then the appeal cannot be filed because government offices are closed. The appeal could then be filed on the day after such non-working public holiday. But again, in the case, this day is a Sunday when government offices are also closed. Thus, the filing on the following Monday. April 23. is still within the ten-day period. (Pacana v. National Labor Relations Commission, et al.. G.R. No. 83513. April 18. 1989) (2) According to the Labor Code (in Art. 223). in the exercise of its appellate jurisdiction over decisions of labor arbiters, a decision of the National Labor Relations Commission is final and executory after ten (10) calendar days from receipt thereof by the parties. In view of the above provision, the employer in the case in the question who is aggrieved by the decision of the NLRC should file a petition for certiorari with the Supreme Court under Rule 65 of the Rules of Court within a reasonable period from receipt of the decision which is the subject of the petition for certiorari usually within 30 days. (Pacana, op.cit)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 250,
        "Question": "Which of the following is cognizable by the Bureau of Labor Relations Med-Arbiters? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "c. Contest for the position of MG Union President brought by Ka Joe, the losing candidate in the recent union elections;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 251,
        "Question": "Distinguish the terms 'conciliation,' 'mediation' and 'arbitration'.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "There is a DOLE official called a 'Conciliator Mediator'. He is an officer of the NCMB whose principal function is to assist in the settlement and disposition of labor - management disputes through conciliation and preventive mediation. However, he does not promulgate decisions that settle controversies about rights, which are demandable and enforceable. The latter is called arbitration and is the function of a labor arbiter or a voluntary arbitrator. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: (1) CONCILIATION is the process of dispute management whereby parties in dispute are brought together for the purpose of: (1) amicably settling the case upon a fair compromise; (2) determining the real parties in interest; (3) defining and simplifying the issues in the case; (4) entering into admissions or stipulations of facts; and (5) threshing out all other preliminary matters (Section 3, Rule V, 2005 NLRC Rules of Procedure). In resolving labor disputes, this comes before arbitration, as a mandatory process, pursuant to the State policy of promoting and emphasizing conciliation as modes of settling labor disputes (Art. 211 (A)(a), Labor Code). (2) MEDIATION is a voluntary process of settling dispute whereby the parties elect a mediator to facilitate the communication and negotiation between the parties in dispute for the purpose of assisting them in reaching a compromise (Sec. 3(q), Rep. Act No. 9285 or the Alternative Dispute Resolution Law). (3) ARBITRATION is a system of dispute settlement that may be compulsory or voluntary, whereby the parties are compelled by. the government, or agree to submit their dispute before an arbiter, with the intention to accept the resolution of said arbiter over the dispute as final and binding on them (Luzon Development Bank v. Association of Luzon Development Employees, 249 SCRA 162 ). In this jurisdiction, compulsory arbitration in labor disputes are submitted to a labor arbiter, whose powers and functions are clearly defined under Article 217(a) of the Labor Code; whereas in voluntary arbitration, the powers and functions of the voluntary arbitrator or panel of voluntary arbitrators elected to resolve the parties’ dispute involve the interpretation and implementation of the parties’ collective bargaining agreement, pursuant to Articles 260-262 of the Labor Code."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 252,
        "Question": "TRUE or FALSE. Answer TRUE if the statement is true, or FALSE if the statement is false. Explain your answer in not more than two (2) sentences.  [e] The visitorial and enforcement powers of the DOLE Regional Director to order and enforce compliance with labor standard laws can be exercised even when the individual claim exceeds P5,000.00. (2009 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "True. The visitorial and enforcement powers of the DOLE Regional Director to order and enforce compliance with labor standards laws can be exercised even when the individual claims exceed P5,000.00 The authority under Article 128 may be exercised regardless of the monetary value involved. Under Article 129, however the authority is only for claims not exceeding P5,000.00 per claimant."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 253,
        "Question": "Tina Aquino, a domestic helper in the household of Fidel Aldeguer, filed an action in the Regional Office of the Department of Labor and Employment. (DOLE) for recovery of unpaid wages amounting to P3.500.00 and PI.499.00 as moral damages. Aquino claimed that the amount of P3, 500.00 is equivalent to the P500.00 a month she failed to receive for the last seven months of her employment with Aldeguer. based on their agreed P2.500.00 monthly salary. Aldeguer moved to have Aquino’s complaint dismissed, alleging that as a domestic helper Ms. Aquino should have first brought the matter to the Lupong Barangay. If you were the Regional Director, how would you resolve the matter?",
        "Answer": "As Regional Director. I will assume jurisdiction. The provisions of P.D. No. 1508 requiring the submission of disputes before the Barangay Lupong Tagapayapa prior to their filing with the court or other government offices are not applicable to labor cases. Article 129 of the Labor Code empowers the Regional Director to hear and decide any matter involving the recovery of wages and other monetary claims and benefits owing to an employee or person employed in* domestic or household service, provided that the money claim does not exceed P5.000.CX). (Montoya vs. Escayo, G.R Nos. 82211-12, March 21. 1989)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 254,
        "Question": "In a letter to the Regional Director of Region VII of the Department of Labor and Employment, employee Ricardo Malalang claims that his employer, the Visayan Sea Products Corp., has not compensated him for various legal benefits, including overtime pay, holiday pay, 13th month pay and other monetary benefits totaling P6.000.00. Despite the fact that the amount claimed exceeds P5.000 how may the Regional Director exercise jurisdiction over the case? Why?",
        "Answer": "The power of the Regional Director over money claims may arise under either Article 128 or Article 129 of the Labor Code. Under Article 129, for the Regional Director to exercise Jurisdiction, the aggregate money claims of an employee should not exceed P5.000.00. Under Article 128, as the duly authorized representative of the Secretary of Labor, the Regional Director has the power to order and administer, after due notice and hearing, compliance with the labor standards provisions of the Labor Code and other labor legislation based on the findings of labor regulation officers made in the course of inspection and issue writs of execution to the appropriate authority for the enforcement of their orders, except in cases where the employer contests the findings of the labor regulation officer and raises issues which cannot be resolved without considering evidentiary matters that are not verifiable in the normal course of inspection. Article 128 applies where the relationship of employer- employee relationship still exists."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 255,
        "Question": "Kevin, an employee of House of Sports, filed a complaint with the DOLE requesting the investigation and inspection of the said establishment for labor law violations such as underpayment of wages, non payment of 13th month pay, non payment of rest day pay, overtime day, holiday pay, and service incentive leave pay. House of Sports alleges that DOLES has no jurisdiction over the employees’ claims where the aggregate amount of the claims of each employee exceeds P5,000.00, whether or not accompanied with a claim for reinstatement. Is the argument of House of Sports tenable? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "b) No, Article 128(b) of the Labor Code shall apply, and thus, the DOLE Regional Director has jurisdiction;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 256,
        "Question": "The Regional Director or his representative may be divested of his enforcement and visitorial powers under the exception clause of Article 128 of the Labor Code and, resultantly, jurisdiction may be vested on the labor arbiter when three (3) elements are present. Which of the following is not one of the three (3) elements? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "c. The issues raised should have been verifiable during the inspection."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 257,
        "Question": "Pursuant to his power under Sec. 278(g) (263(g)) of the Labor Code, the Secretary of Labor assumed jurisdiction over the 3-day old strike in Armor Steel Plates, Inc., one of the country's bigger manufacturers of steel plates, and ordered all the striking employees to return to work. The striking employees ignored the order to return to work. (a) What conditions may justify the Secretary of Labor to assume jurisdiction?  (b) What are the consequences of the assumption of jurisdiction by the Secretary of Labor, and of the disobedience to the return to work? Explain your answer.  (2017 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "(a) The conditions that may justify the Secretary of Labor to assume jurisdiction are found in Article 278(g) (formerly Article 263 (g)), viz: When, in his opinion, there exists a labor dispute causing or likely to cause a strike or lockout in an industry indispensable to the national interest, the Secretary of Labor and Employment may assume jurisdiction over the dispute and decide it or certify the same to the Commission for compulsory arbitration. xxx (b) The assumption of jurisdiction by the Secretary of Labor automatically results in a return-to-work of all striking workers (if one has already taken place) or enjoins the taking place of a strike, whether or not a corresponding order had been issued by the Secretary of Labor (Union of Filipro Employees v. Nestle Philippines, Inc., G.R. Nos. 88710-13). Defiance of the return-to-work order is an illegal act, which constitutes a valid ground for loss of employment status (Manila Hotel Employees Association v. Manila Hotel Corporation, 517 SCRA 349)."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 258,
        "Question": "Philippine Electric Company is engaged in electric power generation and distribution. It is a unionized company with Kilusang Makatao as the union representing its rank-and-file employees. During the negotiations for their expired collective bargaining agreement (CBA), the parties duly served their proposals and counter-proposals on one another. The parties, however, failed to discuss the merits of their proposals and counter-proposals in any formal negotiation meeting because their talks already bogged down on the negotiation ground rules, i.e., on the question of how they would conduct their negotiations, particularly on whether to consider retirement as a negotiable issue. Because of the continued impasse, the union went on strike. The Secretary of Labor and Employment immediately assumed jurisdiction over the dispute to avert widespread electric power interruption in the country. After extensive discussions and the filing of position papers (before the National Conciliation and Mediation Board and before the Secretary himself) on the validity of the union's strike and on the wage and other economic issues (including the retirement issue), the DOLE Secretary ruled on the validity of the strike and on the disputed CBA issues, and ordered the parties to execute a CBA based on his rulings. Did the Secretary of Labor exceed his jurisdiction when he proceeded to rule on the parties' CBA positions even though the parties did not fully negotiate on their own? (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "No. The power of the Secretary of Labor under Article 263(g) is plenary. He can rule on all issues, questions or controversies arising from the labor dispute, including the legality of the strike, even those over which the Labor Arbiter has exclusive jurisdiction. (Bagong Pagkakaisa ng mga Manggagawa sa Triumph International v. Secretary, G.R. Nos. 167401 and 167407, July 5, 2010)"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 259,
        "Question": "Company C, a toy manufacturer, decided to ban the use of cell phones in the factory premises. In the pertinent Memorandum, management explained that too much texting and phone-calling by employees disrupted company operations. Two employees-members of Union X were terminated from employment due to violation of the memorandum-policy. The union countered with a prohibitory injunction case (with prayer for the issuance of a temporary- restraining order) Filed with the Regional Trial Court, challenging the validity and constitutionality of the cell phone ban. The company filed a motion to dismiss, arguing that the case should be referred to the grievance machinery pursuant to an existing Collective Bargaining Agreement with Union X, and eventually to Voluntary Arbitration. Is the company correct? Explain.  (2010 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "YES. Termination cases arising in or resulting from the interpretation and implementation of collective bargaining agreements, and interpretation and enforcement of company personnel policies which were initially processed at the various steps of the plant-level Grievance Procedures under the parties collective bargaining agreements, fall within the original and exclusive jurisdiction of the voluntary arbitrator pursuant to Article 217 (c) and Article 261 of the Labor Code. ALTERNATIVE ANSWER: NO. The Regional Trial Court has jurisdiction to hear and decide the prohibitory injunction case filed by Union X against Company C to enjoin the latter from implementing the memorandum-policy against use of cell phones in the factory. What is at issue is Union X S challenge against the validity and constitutionality of the cell phone ban being implemented by Company C. The issue, therefore, does not involve the interpretation of the memorandum-policy, but its intrinsic validity (Haliguefla v. PAL, 602 SCRA 297 )."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 260,
        "Question": "The State has a policy of promoting collective bargaining and voluntary arbitration as modes of settling labor disputes. To this end, the voluntary arbitrator’s jurisdiction has not been limited to interpretation and implementation of collective bargaining agreements and company personnel policies. It may extend to 'all other labor disputes,' provided (2011 BAR)",
        "Answer": "(B) the parties agreed to such extended jurisdiction."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 261,
        "Question": "J refused to comply with the deployment assignment with K, a manning agency. K filed a complaint against him for breach of contract before the Philippine Overseas Employment Administration (POEA). The POEA penalized J with one (1) year suspension from overseas deployment. On appeal, the suspension was reduced to six (6) months by the Secretary of Labor. Is the remedy of appeal still available to J and where should he file his appeal? (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "a. Yes, he can file an appeal before the Court of Appeals via a Petition for Certiorari under Rule 65;"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 262,
        "Question": "The period to file a notice of appeal to the NLRC is: (2012 Bar Question)",
        "Answer": "a) 3 years [Art. 290, Labor Code]"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 263,
        "Question": "Chito was illegally dismissed by DEF Corp. effective at the close of business hours of December 29, 2009. IV (1). He can file a complaint for illegal dismissal without any legal bar within _________. (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "(B) four (4) years"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Labor Law",
        "No": 264,
        "Question": "IV (2). If he has money claims against DEF Corp., he can make the claim without any legal bar within _________. (2013 Bar Questions)",
        "Answer": "(A) three (3) years"
    }
];
